okay so
I want to talk about
hey I want to talk about the diffusion model so this is
rounding out the generative image parts
I know there was
when I sent out the survey at the beginning of the
class I know there was interest on generative AI
actually I'm not sure if it was mainly just the LLM
stuff which we covered or
also the vision vision stuff
so for diffusion models as I
alluded to last time
so you're not going to get through all of the
you know
all of the details of how diffusion models work
it's just it's very math heavy
ideally I mean
I can imagine a short course just on
generative
image models and diffusion models
there's so much going on
so what I hope to do like
last time is at least give you a sense
you know build some intuition about what's going on
and
you'll have to dive in
and actually if anyone's interested
happy to do a little side project
with you if you want
I can always create
more content
as well
so
also like last time the book at least the way the book
kind of organized things I didn't find it that
accessible and so I'm going to rely heavily on
similar blog
from last time
and I guess these are this might be publicly available
I realize I referenced
towards Data Science because I subscribe
if you don't have access and you
I'm pointing to something that you don't have access
just let me know I can
do it like a
print screen or something
of the site and share it
um oh and then in terms of announcement so did
Xavier reach out to
last time I mentioned you're nodding ahead yet so the
yeah so what I asked them to do is take the
5 people on the top of the leaderboard
so am I
remembering right it's like Andy Jessica Furry Jasmine
who else and you're as well
yeah and so what I ask savior is just organize
just you know collect amongst you
just what your training tactic was and what model
you use and then either
he'll put it together in a slide if there's you know
not a huge difference but let's let's spend a
at least a few minutes 10 minutes or something at the
beginning of next class on Tuesday
that would be interesting
we can learn something
about your approaches and congrats for
being top of the leaderboard to
and I think that's
that's it for announcements
okay so let me give some I'm
going to try to give some context about how
diffusion models work
and then go into a little bit of the theory
but I'm not going to go into all of
the math it's just not
not conducive to try to do it in a lecture format and
I forget who said it but
math is not a spectator sport and so you really
I encourage you to go in and
actually just kind of rederive
either what's in the book or in the
in this blog post
here because even here they
they skip some steps
and I'll certainly skip some steps here
and then I'll talk a little bit about
how you get to training and then flash some application
examples
okay so kind of like last time
you know the idea is that
we're going to
somehow figure out a probability distribution
and we're going to try to
generate new samples from that probability distribution
and the new samples will be
hopefully high quality images
so the way
diffusion models work
is that
they essentially start
kind of like in
with the variational
auto encoders and also Gans
and I'll make the comparison here in a little bit
but
like in the 1D example it starts with just random noise
and basically what you've done
is you Learned a generative model
that can go from a
purely like Galcian random distribution
to some more complicated distribution that reflects
the dataset of images in this case
so the exact same thing
for images is just that you have it's a
much higher dimensional space
but basically
every color of every pixel
you know you have a distribution
multi dimensional distribution
across that so we're going to
try and it you know
just probably like last time it seems counterintuitive
we're gonna start from noise
and somehow we're gonna generate these
these high quality images
so what's interesting
so I
lectured in the slightly reversed order but these three
key papers came out for each of these three
areas just a year apart so in 2013
King Ma and Welling introduced the Variational
Auto Encoder which I talked about
2,014 good Fellow
and others introduced Gans and then 2,015
Saul Dickstein
introduced this paper
it's called Deep Unsupervised Learning using Non
Equilibrium Thermodynamics
wasn't clear from the paper
title that these became the diffusion models
and there been variations of
that since then and of course
there's a lot of commercial so a lot of excitement
especially after
these more efficient versions like stable diffusion
which I'm not going to really go into
I'll mention very briefly at the end
but of course Doli 2 Doli 3
Imagen from Google make a scene from meta
imagine video
so going into video space
from Google and make a video from meta
stable diffusion 3 just came out from stability
AI and then there's a mid journey
that they're on
now their their model version 6
and
and you've seen examples I'll show some
today as well but this is from metasmacosine
that's
generating images from a sketch and a text prompt
they don't show the
input here but
the idea is that you can
you have a lot of creative control now you can
sketch and not just verbally describe
what's going on
okay so what's the basic idea
of these diffusion
models or they call diffusion probabilistic models
so
the idea is you take this and I'll describe what
this stochastic process is
but there's a forward process that you take
in your training
you take all of these high quality images
and you slowly add noise to them where you get to
essentially a fully random image
but you have all of these samples and then
the goal of diffusion models
is you're trying to learn the reverse process
you're basically trying to figure out from a
random sample
can I get back to one step at a time can I get back to
some high quality
high quality image
and you know if it's just
if there's no other information
it'll just come back to something
that's high quality but there's these
conditional diffusion models just like the conditional
Gans and VAEs that you can give it text prompts or
as we saw in the other one like give it
even image input
to kind of guide
how it does this reverse
diffusion process
okay so we're going to
hopefully give you some intuition about
how this works and so I'll start by I'll talk about
what are stochastic processes and
specifically diffusion processes
then give a little bit of
intuition hopefully behind these
diffusion probabilistic models
going to go into a little bit of math
not going to do the complete derivation like I said
and then talk about
how it's trained in practice all right
okay
so let's just to kind of set things up a little bit
when we're talking about stochastic processes
or diffusion processes
we're talking about
random variables
what makes a
random variable a stocastic process is that
you basically have
continuously varying random variable
in the continuous case index by time
or you can have discrete
random variables that are just indexed either by
indexing points of times or just simple simple indexing
and so
yeah so when you have a random variable and you have
a realization of it that's what we call that a sample
you know you have one
example or one sample from the random variable
but for the stochastic process
a realization is a sample path
so over time how did that random variable
kind of
evolve over time
let me show you some pictures
there are
like I said there are discrete time and continues time
random variables
but there's also discrete value
and continuous value so discrete time
let's say you're taking daily average temperature
once a day you're recording average temperature
or coin flipping discrete events
whereas continuous time
you're monitoring the I guess the second by second
stock price
values or you're monitoring Q length
which can change instantaneously but
presumably it's like you know cue of people
it changes by a discrete discrete value so
the you know temperatures
are you know to some precision
are you know basically continuous valued and same
to stock price
but coin flip of course is discrete value
and cue length
if you're counting the number of people or the
number of jobs in your
batch Q on SCC
then they're going to be discrete values but
the cue size can change basically instantaneously
at any point in time
okay so
there's the we're going to use
the
properties of Markoff
process and a Markoff process is basically
it's a stochastic process
but as it says with no memory so that just means that
the current value at the current time
is only dependent on the previous value
so
if it wasn't Markoff process then it
can be dependent on all the previous
values or realizations of the
of the process
but with Markoff
basically
everything you need to know to figure out what's
coming next is in the last sample
okay and so
a diffusion process now is
so it can be described by a stochastic
differential equation
so differential equation is just
something that's
referring like some infinitesimal change of some value
usually versus some other variable like time
but a stochastic
differential process has
a random process inserted as well
and so this is kind of the standard form is here's our
variable that we're trying to predict or measure
you have this thing called the drift coefficient
which is deterministic
but it can be dependent
on the value of your random variable
and the point in time
so it can be varying in a deterministic way
and then you have something called a diffusion
coefficient which can be
dependent on
the value of the random variable in the time
and then it's
the product with a so called wiener process that I'll
describe here
in a minute so
and I'll show some pictures
and again just to emphasize so
the drift coefficient and the diffusion coefficient
are functions of the
value of the random variable in time
okay so
as I said this part here if you just
mask out this this is
just a regular differential equation
but this makes it a stochastic
differential equation
okay so
let's talk about what a Wiener process is
so it's a
continuous time stochastic process that has
these properties generally just by convention
the first sample is 0
it kind of doesn't really matter
where it starts
but it has
independent increments and so has this Markoff
property that
the
two
samples that are
side by side
are independent of all the past samples
okay and then probably the
kind of the key thing to take away here is that
the difference and so if I take
even in the continuous case if I take
two samples and I take the difference
they're going to be normally distributed with
mean of zero
okay so I'm taking so I have this
this meaner process or Browning motion process
I take a sample doesn't matter
even when I take another sample
some later point that difference
is going to be follow this agaussian distribution
with
0 mean
and the variance is just related to
the distance between the samples
kind of I mean you think about it so here's a picture
right here
these are just different
Wiener processes that
start zero and because of the random nature
that of course they'll have different paths
and so you can calculate
the standard deviation
which is just related to
the
distance from the first sample
which is the gray area here and so
it kind of makes sense if it's randomly
jumping up and down in this 1d case
the further away you get
the more likely you are to be farther from zero right
kind of makes sense yep
are
the curves generated differentiable everywhere or
is it
not different differentiable anywhere
it's kind of jagged
yeah
we we are going to be differentiating
so but you know we're going to be
differentiating the equations I guess for the curve
but
I think what you're asking is can you differentiate the
kind of the realizations
I mean because you're referring to
the jagged nature so
I guess
short answer is yes from
analytical perspective
so we're going to you'll see we'll have an expression
for this stochastic differential equation
and and we will be differentiate because it's gonna
well
we're gonna build that into our loss function of a
network that we're going to be training
makes sense
okay
so I do like my
profiles so I threw one in here so
the Weiner process is named after Norber Weiner he's
an interesting character
he was at MIT he's kind of a child prodigy
but he was a you know computer scientist in the
he died in 64 but in the early days
but he was credited with
creating at the time it was called the field of
cybernetics
and so he did a lot of research around these
kind of stochastic processes and these noise processes
and basically they became
key
contributions to
areas in electrical engineering communication
control systems like wiener filter if you ever
looked at control and actually
we use it sometimes in computer vision
and so he was kind of a contemporary or slightly
older but he influenced like John
von Neumann who
famous mathematician and was credited with
inventing the modern
computer architecture
the
CPU kind of architecture it's still called the
von Neumann architecture Today
Claude Shannon who's the
uh basically the creator of uh information theory
or information science
um and so he you know interesting enough he wrote
I put a link here he wrote a
paper in 1949 called The Machine Age
you know again think back to 1949
but anticipating you know
a lot of what's what's happening today around robots
and things like that and there was a
I don't know if you're if you're interested there is a
interesting book it's I guess it's kind of niche but
where they call them the dark hero of the Information
Age
I found it interesting and then the other little tidbit
is that he's my great great grand advisor
so if you do your academic genealogy I'm over the PhD
students probably know what I'm talking about
that
so my advisor was at MIT his advisor
Oppenheim and Schaeffer
they kind of founded the field of
digital signal
processing which
I did my PhD in
and actually
interesting enough there advisor was Amar Bose
founder of Bose Corporation and Bose was a student of
Norbert Wiener so
little bit of trivia
so I feel compelled to understand what he's
done I'm not sure I'm doing it justice but
okay so
let's go back
so we have these
just look at the think about the Wiener process itself
we can take those
samples like a sample that's just some small
time apart from another sample
and as I showed you on the
previous slide
that that difference is always going to be a zero mean
and the standard deviation is always going to be the
basically the distance between
the samples okay
so if you take
samples further apart it's gonna have bigger
standard deviation
that makes sense
okay so we can
discritize
that stochastic differential equation by just
taking two samples and subtracting them
from each other and
that basically so there's a little bit of
assumptions here which I didn't make explicit but
I think
they're assuming that these are kind of slow moving
so these are approximation these are slow moving
curves and so they're not taking account that
these values
might have changed
but it's just factoring in
the difference of the wiener process here
and so it went from this the wiener process to this
this zero mean galcian
okay
at taking the
difference
and then
we can just bring this term
over
here and then
if you have a zero mean
Gaussian and you're multiplying it by some value
you're just changing
you're just creating a new galcian right and so
U becomes U prime
we're multiplying it by something so
this is now just a
galcian 0 mean
but the standard deviation is just the
the constant you know or the value that's
being multiplied here
okay does that
make sense
okay so
let's look at actually going back to the
stochastic differential equation
there's different flavors of the equation plotted here
this line in the middle this dash line in the middle
is just
basically a constant it's just saying that
just for a reference
is just saying that nothing changes
it's actually not
these are the kind of the dash lines are these
non
stochastic
equations just for reference
but if I have no deterministic part and I just have
the Wiener process
then just like before
it's just going to kind of wander around
starting from the zero mean right that's
the equation at the top
this one is
this is a simple differential equation
this dash line here DX equals 2 DT
that
the coefficient
is just
a constant right
the drift
coefficient is just a constant
so
and then here you see that
so you have this it's just kind of growing
you know linearly with time
and then you're adding
the Wiener process on top of it
and then the line down here
now it's getting you know a little bit more you have
the drift coefficient is a simple function
of the random variable itself
and you have something some non
unitary drift coefficient as well for
the purple line here
and so you can see that the
standard deviation because we have a
bigger constant
multiplying the Wiener process
it's kind of wandering around
quite a bit quite a bit more
okay all right so we want to reverse this process
and so we had
the stochastic differential equation
and so here's
where I'm going to start skipping a bunch of math
but you know can encourage you to
do it or we can talk offline
is that we can just define this new variable
X hat
which is just
instead of starting from time
zero and going to like time
capital t
it's X hat we just define it to be
capital t minus t right so if you have
basically one where
we're going to be talking a lot about
time here so probably point to this
that the normal diffusion process like I was showing
is going from zero to time t
and now
X
hat
X hat is going
back that way
so with some manipulations and some substitutions
you can write what looks like
actually there's one thing that's also
a little bit different
here is that the diffusion coefficient
is only dependent on time it's not dependent on the
random variable value itself
but with that
Assumption you can rewrite the
equation and then basically get it in a form
substituting these variables it looks very much like
just another stochastic differential equation
okay
and this term here has a
special name the gradient of log
of the probability distribution of the random variable
is called the score function
whereas the
the probability of the random variable is just
the marginal probability
okay so
it turns out that
if you have this
this kind of stochastic differential equation
that if you carefully pick your
drift coefficient your diffusion coefficient
that you can start with any kind of distribution
over here
and basically
you can guarantee
that if you take enough steps that you will end up
at some point with a just a pure
Galcian distribution so you
this is so it's an equation
that you know essentially diffuses the
your complicated distribution
to a simple Galcian
distribution
and this is the
form of the equations that will be used in the
diffusion modeling
I warned you guys it can be a lot of math right
ah
okay so
let's develop a little bit more intuition
so we had this form like I showed you here
and so if you picket the values
of this form and P is between 01 you'll have this
property and you can take
step by step you can substitute for
every subsequent step
like for example
at the final step over here
of course the equation is simply just the previous step
and then you just keep going back
another step and substitute back in there
and then when you
do all of that you end up with equation
like this which is kind of of the same form you have
your first sample value
over here
and then you just have this kind of sum
of like the square root of square to 1 minus p
raised to the I power
of the summation
but they're all just multiplying
one of these
Gaussian
these normal distribution random variables and so
when you're of course when you're multiplying something
like a normally distributed random variable something
all you're doing is you're just changing
the variance of that
random variable
so you can
view this as simply just a sum of independent Gaussians
which you can then just add up all the
standard deviations to get just a single Gaussian
okay so
if you do that for large enough step sizes
then the
value here
as Tegos Infini is eventually going to go to zero
and this is just a geometric series here
if you're looking at the variance
so you square the terms inside here
as t goes infinity
that this just collapses into
this close form representation from the
geometric series
and as t goes infinity this just becomes
1 and so this tells you that
again this diffusion process works analytically
you take enough steps
you're eventually going to get through just a unit
standard Calcium
okay and that's what we're doing but
for images okay you start
here with a picture it already looks a little noisy
picture of a cat
and then you're just adding adding noise
to the point where
at some point you basically just have a
Gaussian random noise distributed
image and for every step
it's just that equation that I that I showed you
so actually the forward pass
you don't have to learn anything you can just use this
process is that you're adding
noise in this kind of
structured structured way step by step
okay so
the question is
so why
use this
seemingly complicated process
so it turns out that
it gives us this kind of
structured way
of going step by step to go from
any complex distribution
to a standard
normal distribution
and it does it in a way and hopefully
I'll show you enough
to convince you that
it does it in a way that you can learn the reverse
process
um
and generally
it's really easy
to go
from a original image to just a pure noise image right
you can just
go through that process but it is it's hard to
go the other way
but
if you think about it
you do get some clues like maybe this first step
is difficult when you just have pure noise
but you know maybe you're getting something
that looks like a image
but those clues kind of influence
what happens
now it's maybe just a little bit easier because
you're starting to get to some sample in your
space
and then it generally can get
easier as
you progress
and in fact that's kind of key to this so you can
write it in a closed form like that
the forward pass which is not
trained you just apply that equation
you know you can just take the
composition of all those functions
and you could write a big function
that tries to
go from random noise to your
you know final image
but it's a really hard
you know
probably impossible thing to do first of all can be
very large function
but it also probably doesn't
behave well from a kind of a gradient perspective
you kind of have like one
shot to
to try to learn this model whereas
when you do it
in this step by step
each of these mappings here
what usually happens is this is learning
kind of a course
step first and then as the image gets better
it's learning kind of finer and finer
updates to get to the
the final image that seems to be helping
and it also turns out that the nature of this function
can be the same it's just a
I'll show you
it can be just like a unit or a transformer model
and so you're just
adapting
there's some parameterization
you know like just the time
step that's changing
and so you can actually reuse weights you know learn
a function G
that takes as the image as its input
the noisy image and the time step
and it's that same model
with just different inputs and different time steps
and so it turns out to be much more efficient
just in terms of the number of parameters
and the size of the model
so and that's basically what it's
saying here
so
for these
multi step process just that the gradient descent
is better behaved
OK
yeah this is the point that I just made before is that
this we can have the exact same
so now these aren't different
transforms these are exact same transforms
and they're just
the arguments to them are just the image
that's going in and the which step
that we're on
so we can reuse the process
so
in a lot of ways
it's similar to
variational auto encoders
with some key differences so it is
it's going from
the encoder or the diffusion
forward diffusion is going from a
complex distribution to a simple
so like the encoder and the
in the VAE
and it's learning decoder to go in the other
direction
to produce a
you know a sample that looks like something from your
sample set but
as I mentioned that unlike VAE this is a multistep
process
the encoder is fixed
so we're not actually learning the encoder like in VAE
and
we're using this diffusion process to train
the other big thing is that in VA
remember we were
shrinking the latent space was a smaller dimension
but it's key here that the model at each step
has the exact same size input
as it has output
okay
all right so I'm
just going to get a little bit
deeper but I'm not going to go through all the math
anyone see
the problem with the
what is it what do you see
yeah
so it's still again doing a lot better with words but
not
perfect
okay again I'm not going to go through all of the
all of the math here but
all right so
we're going to assume that we're going to operate in
t discrete steps
and we're going to assume that these are Markoff
processes and so they only depend on
the step before in
either direction
and so
we can define the so called transition probability
that basically says
okay at a current time stamp
current sample
there's a distribution
this conditional distribution is saying that
if I take a new sample given the previous sample
that it's going to be
a normal distribution
and this is reminiscent of that that equation
that I showed you right because
it's just going to be
the mean
is going to be centered around your last sample
with that
weighting that I showed you in that previous equation
and
the variance were just multiplying that
the previous value by
some value beta
and so that's going to influence the variance
or standard deviation
and this gives us
a way to do a trade off between
basically how much information to keep from the
previous sample
yeah and so
we can for this next sample
we can say because you know this is the trick we use
I guess a number of times now
with these Gaussian random variables is if you take
the previous random variable at t minus 1
you multiply by something
well actually this is a deterministic value
if you take the
some random process
and you multiply it by something
you're just changing the
standard deviation and shifting it so this
is equivalent to
this up here right
we're just
shifting it and changing the standard deviation
okay
so we can go all the way from step zero
two step t
in kind of this closed form
but it just becomes the product
of all of those
equations and so you have
essentially those the one minus betas
that were here
this is just previous step
we can just
multiply all those out right and then you have the
you have the product
of those terms right so
if you want to go figure out
the probability
over all the steps
you just multiply
each step
going back right
so it turns out that
with the
the choices of the drift and the
diffusion coefficient
that you can write
the
transition probability
the probability of the previous sample
so now we're going back the other way
you can write it in a very similar way
so now this is the important
direction because we have to figure out
we have to learn this we want to
denoise
go back this way
and so we can write in this form but
it's going to be based on some
function that's going to determine the mean and some
function that's going to determine the covariance
and we don't know what those are
yeah but let's assume that they're parameterized but
they're basically
we can use deep learning models to do that
okay so
you can do the same thing now in the reverse direction
if you're trying to do
over the whole sequence it's just a product of
all of those
conditionals right going back
and
yeah and it just
the starting term here
was not dependent on time it's just a regular Calcium
okay so
you know with a
little leap of faith here we have the
function going forward
this forward process which is
we don't have to learn it it's just defined here
and now we have this reverse process
and at least we have a
description for the probability distribution
but it's based on some
parameters here that we have to learn
so ah
yeah so question is how do we learn those parameters
and you know
we're going to we want to train a deep learning model
so how do we define the loss function
remember
well we had a we defined a
or you can think of a probability distribution
when you're training
you have these example
you know your data set
so you have a probability distribution
the original model
and then you're going all the way to the noise
and then when you come back
we have this probability
distribution of our
our denoising process
and the goal is to make this look like
this right so we want
the
result of our denoising the probability distribution
we want it to look like
the distribution of our
dataset of our sample set right and so
how do we
compare probability distributions
what's the measure yeah
Chao divergence yeah yeah and so
similar to like in the VAE
we're going to
build a loss function that
is going to try to find
the
models
the parameterized models for the mean and the variance
so that the divergence
from the actual distribution
to the Learned
denoised distribution is minimized and
this is where I'm going to wave my
wave my hands
I'm going to skip a lot more math you can thank me
but
you know if you go through there's a bunch of tricks
and again suggest you
try this if you're interested but
I just captured some of the tricks here
expanding the probability
sub theta
use Jensen's inequality and so the
the equation for that divergence
you can use Gensis inequality find
a upper bound that's simpler
and so if you minimize the upper bound
simpler equation you're minimizing the actual
equation so the book also
talks about this as well
there are some manipulations with base theorem
you can take advantage of the properties that the
Chao divergence
that both of these are Gaussian distributions and so
you can there are some properties of
kale divergence measures of two calciums that you
you can use
and then there's actually another simplification
suggested by
Ho Adal in this paper of 2020
that simplified it
even more just kind of
I guess
I don't know if he guessed but it's not analytically
derive but it turns out that it
actually works even a little bit better
than the
analytical derivation and so
the forward process again
was what I showed you
this reverse process where we have to learn
these parameters
and then this kind of the near final
it's like the simplified
it was the upper bound with Jensen's inequality
and then this other step but it's basically
what's kind of interesting here is
what is trying to do it
every step is trying to minimize the noise
measures of the
sample
that's coming in
and the noise that you're producing
okay
so we can
we can leave the
the math for the most part
okay so
it's very involved how to get in the training process
but I'm going to
summarize it at a high level
so again maybe you got some intuition and
I did ask Xavier I didn't find a good
small example I think he
did he
he showed some
a VAE and Gan example right
anyone go to the discussion
section yeah so I asked them to do a
diffusion example for
next week we'll see if you can find
a good simple example
but the idea is basically this and so
this is the training process
so you start with a sample image
and you have noise
and basically you generate a random step
by adding the
noise to the image
and then you do a
you try to take a guess at what the
image would look like
from this noisy image from
through this parameterized model
and from that you're estimating the noise of the
noisy image
for the gradient descent step
you have the estimated noise
and a measure of the true noise
and you calculate gradient descent which I didn't cover
more involved but you can update the model parameters
when you do that and there's some pseudocode there
at the top kind of saying the similar thing
so when you sample it after you train
the process is like this so you start step 1
so you just start with pure random noise
you're estimating
so you're using this
model that you've Learned to estimate the noise of the
current state
you take a first best guess of some image
that's not going to look very good
and then you do a linear combination
between the current state and the estimated noise
from the original sample
to create a new sample
and basically you just you keep doing that
through that transform
and then you'll progressively get
better
that's the pseudocode code for it
but so the model you can use just
you can just use the good old unit
the old encoder decoder
architecture with some kind of time embedding
unit is nice because you have the exact same
resolution of your input to your output right
that's one of the requirements
I think this is
literally the
size of the model
the thing that's I'm not sure
when it was added but there is
these residual blocks
the normal residual blocks from unit right
so you these are
convolutional layers
and then you have these residual
connections that get added in when you're
doing the decombolution side
but they also added these
residual blocks with self attention
so kind of interesting
so taking a little bit from the transformer
architecture
and putting a
self attention
head and I don't know I have to check
or you guys can check
how many
if it's multiheaded attention or not
but that you know
the complicated part was
is deriving the the loss function
you know once you have the loss function
the model architecture itself is
not complicated
and yeah so basically
you train that model it has the time step
that's coming in but you're just running that model at
at every step
this is actually the reverse process
even though it's going to the right
and there's but you can imagine
there's just been a ton of
innovation and experimentation here
I'll show you a couple examples but
they
trying lots of even transformer base
down here yeah it's the exact same model
so but
it's getting the the time index coming in
so it has the
of course different input
and then I think it's
kind of showing it here there's a time in bedding
that's incorporated
as well and I'm
not exactly sure offhand how but is that your question
yeah so text
is conditional generation
so
the yeah so indeed it didn't
it didn't incorporate any kind of you know external
you know additional prompting
and so you know there's
of course a lot of variants here
but I
call out two of them is there's classifier guidance
like
I showed on the was it the VAE or Gan lecture now but
where you're incorporating class information
and you're influencing the reconstruction based on
class and I'll show you a picture example or
guidance from text
and basically
what you're doing is you're incorporating
you're using a
language model
like a transformer
to create an embedding
and then
you're adding that you're injecting that
into the flow and I think I have a picture
here
but
and then there's
other
examples like I mentioned at the very beginning that
you can also like show it a sketch and text
you know so there's
variations here but here's
this is this paper by Darry Wall and nickel
that's doing again its image net
and is just taking the
Imagenet class as guidance here
and so you can imagine
that it didn't put the labels here
this is an example from the book but
you can kind of guess what the class labels are
and it's doing
high quality
generation
so but yeah so for
text this is one example this is Saharia
and it's pretty recent 2022 but
this is taking a language model
but it's also doing this
hierarchical this kind of cascaded so it does
low resolution
and then that feeds into a slightly higher resolution
and then that feeds into a
slightly higher resolution
as well but you see
the embedding vectors are injected and I
I don't no offhand the
exact architecture but you can imagine that it's
being added you know at the
at some of the layers I mean
for unit it's probably being
remapped into
two dimensional
kind of feature vector so that it can be
added in or it could be
you know weighted across channels or something
you have to look at the paper to see exactly how
but of course
yeah so lots of examples now
this was again from
the Saharia paper but
and I guess okay this is
imagine this is the Google model
and so yeah I'm not going to go into it here but
stable diffusion
really kicked off because
it was more efficient and slightly higher
higher quality
but it's using
a you know encoder decoder with attention
kind of architecture
and I guess it's not really
showing it here I mean this is like their overall
diagram
maybe it's
kind of represented here but it's reducing the size
into kind of like a smaller embedding space
denoising and then
upscaling
to
the higher resolution
but and it's also
able to condition on images
some other representation some kind of semantic map
or text so you could condition it on
a lot of different things and
it seems to work well
so I thought I'd throw this picture in because
I was trying to create
create it and I wasn't successful
and I think the way it failed is kind of
interesting so on Dolly 3 now
they have this new feature
so my original prompt was this
so I wanted to use it as the transition in the slide
where it's a
Victorian butcher addressed
cranking a meat grinder but
math symbols are going in and
nice pictures are falling out and so actually what
this is not my first iteration
but it was actually
ground meat look kind of disgusting
so I didn't include that picture
so the
interesting thing about Dolly 3 now is that you can
go into it and you can actually select
part of the image and so
and this is where diffusion models also
one of their strengths is in painting so
I just selected all of the ground meet here
and then I tried it again
and by the way remember in Dolly 3
behind the scenes
it's creating a much more detailed
so it's using an LLM
actually using gpt4
to create a very detailed
prompt that it
doesn't even show you unless you kind of click
click on the info button
so it's interesting how it's
you know they've trained this more detailed prompt
and even on the detailed prompt it is saying
that you know
that I want
math symbols going in and pictures coming out
and I even
mask this and told it to do it again
but you know you can think that
at least in the probability distribution
apparently it was so far out of the
distribution of having a meek grinder doing math
I just couldn't get it
I couldn't steer it
you know out of this mode kind of realistic
it did draw a lot of symbols on the meek grinder
itself funny enough
I didn't ask it to
but I think it's kind of indicative of
that you know you're playing with these distributions
and you know I could not get it out of the
you know the more
central mode of you know a picture of a
Victorian butcher with a meek grinder
but you can imagine so in painting is kind of an easy
conditioning process right
so you just mask out this area
you just provide the rest of the image with the mask
the masked area
and then just do
noise and diffusion on
that part conditioned on everything else
so it has a lot of flexibility and of course
they're using it for music and
everything else as well
okay so if you want to
this here's the link again
let me know if you don't have access to the blog post
I think it
helps make the chapter a little bit more readable too
and then there's a CVPR
2023 last year
there was a
tutorial
like a five hour tutorial if you want to go
it starts from
you know like where I started
but it goes pretty quickly into the
into more details there's
another version the next version at CVPR this year
they're doing it again as well
all right so okay so that's it for diffusion so next
time
I'm doing graph neural networks
and then
reinforcement learning
and again I'm gonna try to focus on like
rlhf because I know
these half the class has taken reinforcement learning
so and then please for the
leaderboard people work with Xavier
and get that slider 2 together
all
right thank you