All right, so today we're back
on the book chapter.
I think the treatment
of graphenolormat
works was just fine,
so I actually follow it very closely.
And it's more, I think,
straightforward extension
from what we've been talking about earlier,
opposed to the, oops, I forgot to move the,
you are here pointer.
But yeah, a little bit more straightforward extension
from the neural net stuff,
from the GANS and diffusion
models and VAE.
So I think, so I will keep
the final report and repo here.
I guess technically, I think,
Osama, you're right,
because there's no final.
You know, they want me to start
doing grades after the last class,
but it seems like it's not
strictly enforced.
And so this gives you some more
time
to clean things up.
See why it's not.
So I only have two volunteers
for the 25th.
Thank you to the both of you.
So tonight I'm going to randomly
select
the other six, I guess, for the 25th.
And then everyone else
will go on the 30th.
And so I'll let you know.
The other thing is I updated,
everyone see the final project info.
I updated on the website
and grade scope.
So I put a little bit
more
instruction on the video.
I updated the report template,
the LaTeX template,
and I put a comment, a little bit more detail
on the GitHub repo.
So in the report, if you could put
a link to the repo,
you can put it on grade scope.
I also had it as well.
But the idea is that, I mean,
like any kind of well-executed project,
ideas to make it reproducible,
and so somebody can come
and reproduce your work
is the kind of ideal case.
Any questions about final projects,
presentations?
All right, so let's jump in.
So graph neural networks.
I think this is an interesting space,
not something that I had really
worked in before.
But like I said, it's a pretty
straightforward extension.
So the main challenges
is that the topology of the graph can vary,
the types of connections
in which nodes are connected,
the size of these graphs
can be quite large.
And we have to deal with a case
where you have a single monolithic graph,
which is, I'll show a bunch of examples,
but that's a pretty common case.
And so we'll talk about
what does it mean to do batches of data
because you need that for stochastic
gradient descent, for example.
So I'll cover definitions.
We'll talk about representation,
the so-called adjacency matrix,
which is kind of crucial
for describing the topology of the graph,
and then get into the graph
neural networks,
how you build a convolutional layer
on top of a graph,
and then how you build graph classification
and regression
at the graph level
and the node level.
Yeah, I just realized that I had also mentioned
we're going to do
a little recap of the project.
Maybe we'll push it to Thursday.
Okay.
All right, so basic definition
and examples.
So generally, so the nodes,
sometimes they're called vertices,
are connected by edges or links.
You can have undirected
where there's no kind of implied direction
between the nodes,
or you can have directed.
And if you do have a directed connection,
if there's no cycles,
nothing going back upon itself,
then you can have a directed
acyclic graph.
And so sometimes you'll hear the term DAG
because there's certain things
that you can do with DAGs
if they have those two properties.
So we have been looking at,
we didn't really treat it
as a graph per se,
but we have been looking
at directed acyclic graphs.
Just the feed-forward neural network
is one example.
But it's, you know, I guess
kind of a regular topology.
We didn't treat it as a graph.
I also mentioned this in the VAE talk,
these Bayesian probabilistic
graphical models
that you can represent something like this,
where you have like a node
that represents a variable.
And so typically you have something
like a prior probability
with a directed edge
to another variable.
And then that node is representing
the conditional probability,
the probability that this takes on some value
given some latent variable in this case.
So in the book there's a bunch
of examples as well.
So road networks are graphs
where the physical locations
or the landmarks are the nodes.
Roads are the edges.
Chemical molecules are examples
where the nodes are atoms
and the edges are chemical bonds between them.
You can have electrical circuit as graphs.
The nodes are components
or the junctions.
And then the edges
are the wires connecting them.
Some other examples.
Social networks,
and this is where
it can be a very large graph.
So you can take all of Facebook
as a social network.
The nodes are the people
and the edges are people
who have friended each other on the platform.
Scientific literature,
the nodes
are the papers, citations,
so these are directed, generally acyclic,
where it's citing password.
And then there's, I'm not aware
of actually much use here
of something like a knowledge graph,
but you can have this kind of hybrid graph.
Actually, in this case, yeah,
these are all directed.
But it is acyclic.
Actually, in the book I think
it says
it's acyclic,
if I remember right,
but I see one cycle right there.
And actually, yeah.
So in this case, you're trying to,
the edges correspond to kind of relationships
between entities that are the nodes.
So you can also, things
that are maybe not,
you wouldn't typically think of as graphs,
but if you have a 3D geometry
of a physical object,
like in this case a plane,
the vertices in 3D
can be the nodes
and then they could just,
you could just have connections
to all the nodes nearby.
There's also, there's a scene graph,
which can be used in 3D rendering,
but it's typically, it describes
the relationship of 3D objects
and these can be hierarchical.
So you can have, in this case,
like a room description
where you have the connection
between
like the back walls connected
to the right wall and the left wall
and the ceiling and the floor.
And then you have a hierarchy,
so you can then have a lampshade,
which is broken further down into components
or you can have the table,
which is broken further down as well.
I put some links of papers that,
some of them are applying neural networks
to these kinds of scene graphs.
And then there's a bunch
of other examples.
So Wikipedia, where articles
are the nodes
and the hyperlinks are the edges.
Computer programs,
you can show as graphs.
In fact, in the example that I did
with the Jupiter notebook
for the micrograd,
we were basically building
a tensor compute graph,
right, if you remember.
So, but yeah, so proteins can be,
the proteins are the nodes,
the edges are where the proteins interact,
and then you can even have
like sets
or lists
or even images
where you just have
the six or eight neighboring pixels
just connected to a particular pixel
as well, okay?
All right, so how do we describe these?
Typically, we're going to define something
called like a node embedding.
So we talked about embedding
vectors
with transformers.
There's actually some analogies there,
which we'll see later,
but you can have some kind of information
that you have
basically translated
into an embedding vector, for example.
Typically, they're all
of the same dimension.
You can also do the same thing with edges.
So you can have an edge embedding
or embedding vector for every edge.
And then typically,
we'll define
an adjacency matrix.
And the way you read this
is that this is just, in this case,
for undirected graphs,
that you just read the indices.
And so if there's a non-zero,
for example, here at 3, 1,
that means there's a connection
between 3 and 1 on the nodes.
And because it's undirected,
then you would expect
there's going
to be a connection on 1, 3.
So it's going to be symmetric,
always a symmetric matrix,
but the diagonal is typically zero
because there's no, at least, external edge
connecting back to itself.
So you see the diagonals are zeros,
and then we have non-zeros,
actually typically just put a 1
where there's a connection.
And these can be very sparse,
but sometimes you'll use sparse
representation
for the matrices.
Okay, so we could take
all of the node data edges,
and then we can put them
into a matrix, right?
So remember, we have
a d-dimensional
embedding vector
for every node,
and we have, let's say, n nodes.
In this case, yeah,
it lines up six nodes.
And so just like we were doing
for transformers,
you can put together an input matrix,
that is just d-dimension
and then n columns,
one column for every node.
Okay?
And then the same thing
for the edges.
You can have a different
dimensionality
to the edges,
but they represent each one of these edges.
And so there's, you know, it's probably
some kind of metadata here,
but these are the connections
that they represent.
Okay? Okay, so let's look at some properties
of the adjacency matrix.
In this case, this is a simple
undirected graph
with eight nodes.
And so you can, I guess
the font's a little bit small,
but you can convince yourself
that there's a one everywhere
where there's a connection on the graph.
And so we can describe one of the nodes
as just a one-hot encoded vector, right?
And so like node six
is just a vector,
the length, this should be length eight,
and then there's just a,
it's all zeros except a one
at the sixth position there, right?
So, and then once you do that,
you can left multiply the embedding vector,
the one-hot vector here
by the adjacency matrix.
And what that gives you,
just think about it, right?
You're taking each row
and then
you're multiplying here.
So you're just pulling out
the whatever column is non-zero.
In this case, you're just pulling
out
the sixth column here.
And remember on the adjacency matrix,
this is saying that for the sixth node,
these are the nodes
that it's connected to, right?
And so it's telling you
that these are,
just by doing this multiplication,
it's telling you those are the neighboring nodes
to the node that we're interested in.
And then you can do it again.
You can left multiply again
by another A adjacency matrix.
And now what it's showing you
is that all of the nodes
is you can reach in exactly two steps.
And you can hit a node twice,
but you see like seven is not lit up,
it's not colored
because you can't get there
in exactly two steps.
It's not up to two steps,
it's exactly two steps
that it's describing.
Okay?
And so if you just multiply A by itself,
what this is telling you
is that,
I write it here,
that if you raise A to whatever power,
for example of two,
just multiply it by itself
that many times,
then every position here,
it contains the number of, as it says here,
unique walks of that length
that you raise the power to,
the number of unique walks
from node N to N.
So if you look here, let's say one, two, three, four, one, two, three,
well, okay, that's probably, well, yeah, this is saying
from four to four,
you can, there should be
four unique walks,
steps of two, right?
Is that, I don't see the fourth one.
Does anyone see the fourth one?
Oh, it's three, three, okay, yeah.
Okay, yeah, and so the,
but the thing to remember here
is that this, that value,
that it's not the number
of unique paths,
so you can visit the same node,
but what you can think about
is kind of an upper bound,
but it means that there is some path
up to the value here
that, with the connection.
So there can be different distance
walks between the nodes.
Okay.
Okay, so now you can do,
you can do some things,
like for example, I just created
a tiny graph
with these node embeddings,
three dimensional node embeddings,
which you can put together
into a node data matrix,
and then this should be the adjacency matrix
for that, for that graph.
You can define a permutation matrix,
and the permutation matrix
just has a one in each column and each row,
so you can't have more than one,
in a column or a row,
but if you take that data matrix
and you right multiply it,
you're basically just permuting these, right?
So, same thing again,
you're just taking the rows
and you're just grabbing
for each of these columns,
you're just grabbing one of the columns out,
and so this permutation matrix here
is just permuting the values of the data matrix there,
and so you can do the same thing to the adjacency matrix,
but you have to post multiply and premultiply
by the transpose,
and so you can, hopefully I did this right,
so I permuted it,
I left the old indices,
these are the new indices,
I renumbered them,
they're just different numbers,
but they still have the same value,
they're the same topology,
they're just indexed differently,
but the new adjacency matrix
should be correct for this.
So, yeah, let me talk
about some properties
and then we'll go back
to the permutation
adjacency matrix.
So, how do we extend this
to a graph neural network?
Essentially what we're going to do
is we're going to take
those node embedding matrices
that I showed you
and the adjacency matrix
which describes the topology of the graph,
and we're going to pass them
through layers of a neural network.
So, the node embeddings
are updated at each layer,
so you have these kind of hidden representation
or hidden activations
after each layer,
and of course when you start
the input data
is just the embedding vector
of each node,
but at the end you have this output
which is, you know, you have a representation
for each node,
but now it's incorporated context, you know,
from its neighbors in the rest of the graph
because as you'll see, well, we're going to kind of aggregate information
from the neighboring nodes.
And so, yeah, interestingly,
this is kind of like word embeddings
in a transformer,
you know, when you start out you just have
a unique word embedding
for every word or token,
but as it travels through the transformer
that what you have at the end
is you have, you know,
kind of something
that represents the word in its context
to the other words in the sentence.
Okay.
Okay, so you can do,
just like other neural networks,
we can create classification
and regression networks with these,
and so, you know,
some examples, for example,
you can give it a molecular structure
and graph form
and then you can try to figure out
if it's poisonous or not
based on the chemical structure,
or you can regress boiling
and freezing points,
so two regression values
out of a molecular graph.
Yeah, and so generally,
just like
with other neural networks
that we saw,
that you can put a head
to the network, right,
so you can put a classification head
or a regression head
at the end of the network
to get it into that kind of final regression
or classification form
and I'll show you some examples.
So I'm going to start
with just the head of the network
and then I'll build up
to how you build the network itself,
but imagine you had a graph
with node embeddings.
We're going to focus mostly on node,
kind of the node data.
At the very end, I'll show
there's kind of a simple way
to handle data in the edges as well,
the edge embeddings,
but let's focus on the node embeddings first.
So let's say you put it
through some neural network,
which we haven't defined,
but you have, on the output,
you're going to have some,
you know,
activations or embeddings
associated with each node
and then you can combine it.
You can put it through a linear layer
and then you can put it
through,
for example,
a sigmoid
or a softmax
or something like that
and then you can end up
with probabilities
for every class.
So here's an example
for just binary classification.
It's just kind of what should
look
pretty familiar.
You have the sigmoid,
you have a beta, a bias here,
and then you have the weights
and this one is just a d-dimensional row vector
and then you have the, you know,
your embeddings matrix here
and so this is just multiplying every,
it's just weighting every column, right,
of your embedding matrix.
But then in this case, because
we want
to get a single output,
we have this one vector, right?
This is just a, I think this is a, yeah, typo here.
This is just a column of ones, right?
And this has the effect
of basically summing,
well, because we're dividing
by the number of vectors,
this has the, basically,
it's just taking the average
of every one
of those vectors and so,
and collapsing it into a single value.
And so this is like mean pooling,
like we showed you before, early.
Okay, and so that was at the graph level.
So we collapsed everything
into a single value.
But you can also do it
at the node level.
So, for example,
you can do
binary classification,
you can decide between, let's say,
one of two kinds of nodes here
and it's very similar
except you're doing it
on every embedding vector.
This is not the matrix,
the whole matrix
of all the embedding vectors stacked.
This is just the individual node vector
indexed by the node number n.
And then so you're doing that now
and you're producing a vector
and then you have a, actually, this is a scale
or you're adding the bias
and then you're getting the value
just for that particular node.
Okay, does that make sense?
Okay, yeah, so here's an example
where you can decide,
let's say you have,
in some cases,
maybe an edge doesn't exist
and you're trying to predict
if an edge should exist there.
And so here you can take
the, essentially,
the dot product
of the neighboring node
embedding vectors,
send it through a sigmoid
and then you can train it
to basically give you the probability
that, in fact, this edge should be there.
It's kind of another example.
Okay? Okay, so let's build up the,
those were the heads of the graph,
let's build up the body
of the graph itself.
Just like we saw before when we were,
it seemed like a long time ago now,
when we were building up
the deep neural networks,
that we're just going to create
all of these hidden layers.
We're going to start with the input.
We now have the adjacency matrix,
but we have parameters for each layer.
We're just going to have
a bunch of hidden layers
and then we're going to, you know,
end up with that final hidden layer
before we get to the head
of the network.
And so we're going to define
what this function f is
to create the next hidden layer.
Okay, so just like
in the convolutional networks
and some of the other networks,
that we do care about equivalence
and invariance.
And so remember, equivalence
means that if I do,
if I transform the input somehow,
that the output is transformed
the same way.
And so remember back
to the permutation matrix,
I can right multiply my data matrix
by the permutation back to left
multiply and right multiply
the adjacency matrix.
But if I do that, then the output
is just the hidden layer
with the same permutation, right,
multiplied by the same permutation matrix.
And so it's equivariant to permutation.
And then invariant, if we're doing
something like sigmoid,
since we're summing
all of these up anyway,
we don't really care
if we're shuffling
the order of the nodes.
And so in this case, if we're doing
like graph level classification,
it's invariant to permutation as well.
So that's a valuable thing
for the graph neural networks.
Okay, so let's now build out
a convolutional layer for the graph.
And so I'm going to define a function here,
the aggregation function.
And essentially what it's doing,
you can see here
that for a particular node
and a particular layer,
okay, that I'm just taking the neighborhood.
So NE is just saying
that it's returning the indices
of all the neighboring nodes
for the node,
not including itself.
Okay, so that's going to be handy.
And then the whole layer itself
is we have a weight matrix.
We're going to multiply it by the node,
the embedding vector
for the node itself,
but we're also going to multiply it
against the sum of all the neighbors as well.
So it's kind of like the convolution, right?
We're taking weights
and we're weighting
all of the neighborhood
around a pixel in that case.
Okay, does that make sense?
And we're using the same weights for both.
So there's already some weight
sharing happening here.
And those same weights
are going to be applied
to every node in that graph at that layer.
Just like in a convolutional network.
Okay, so, yeah, so if you have, in this case,
you have your input,
you have,
after the first layer,
so you do the aggregation
for each node,
you have an omega-zero weight matrix,
and then put it through an activation
and you get the first hidden unit output,
the embeddings at each node.
And then you can do this
through a bunch of layers
until you get to the last layer
and then you just do it again
at the last layer.
So it should look a lot like
the regular neural nets
and the convolutional neural nets
that you saw.
Okay, so we have this equation
where we had the aggregates,
we have this weight matrix,
we applied it to the node
embedding vector,
the sum of all the neighbors.
And then, so, if you do this
to the entire,
you can do this to just the embedding
vector of a node,
but you can also just stack them all together,
like the data matrix
that I was showing you.
So capital H here.
And what you see is that
you're applying it to the same,
yeah, so I guess the first thing
that's important to note here
is that remember when we right-multiplied
by the adjacency matrix,
we got all of the immediate
neighbors
of the node, right?
And so we're replacing
the aggregate function
with this right-multiply by the adjacency matrix.
And so now we have the hidden
layer
embedding matrix
showing up twice
and so we can just factor it out
and then we have the equation here.
And so you can do it in matrix form
on the whole data matrix.
And then you just have the adjacency
plus this is the identity matrix here.
So the nice thing is that this
is equivariant to permutations.
It can handle an arbitrary
number
of neighbors.
So that's all handled
in the adjacency matrix.
We don't have to deal with any kind
of weird indexing or anything.
And it is, you know,
the adjacency matrix
is describing the graph structure
so it can exploit any kind
of graph structure.
And then we are sharing parameters
across every one of the nodes.
So we have that kind of efficiency
of parameters as well.
Okay, so let's put it all together
now
in graph and node classification.
And there are, I'm going
to release a few notebooks.
They're pretty straightforward,
but I think it just helps
to have a little experience
with the Python code
and the matrices
and the indexing a little bit.
And so the one example
you're going
to see in the Python notebook,
maybe it's, yeah, 13.
2 notebook, is that, so
you can put it all together.
You can put a sigmoid head on it
like this with mean pooling.
And then we can do,
for example, classification.
And so in this case, there's 118 elements.
And so we can just have
a one-hot encoded
for every node
to describe which element it is.
And then the first parameter,
we can decide what embedding
dimension we want
so that first weight matrix here
can just be d by 118.
So we switch to some
d-dimensional embedding.
And then we have the weight matrix,
which is a 1 by d row vector as well.
But with that, you can put it all together
and now you basically have
a graph classification network
for, I guess, molecular compound detection.
All right, so let me define
another term here.
So the stuff we've been talking
about up to date with supervised learning
has been these inductive kind of models.
And so typically what we do
is we split our data
into training and test data.
So we have separate data.
We can hold out test
and validation data.
And then we can train on the training data
and then test on the testing data.
But with graphs, you have this case
where you can have
this transductive kind of model,
where you might have a case
where you know the labels
of some of the nodes,
but you don't know some
of the other nodes.
But you can do this kind
of like semi-supervised learning
is that you can still train
with this network
and just your loss function
is just incorporating
your labeled nodes.
And so at training time,
you're not taking into account
because we don't know the labels
on these unknown nodes.
But we can still proceed with training.
But then at inference time,
you could run inference
on these unlabeled nodes.
So that's the transductive model.
So think about this example here
where you want to do binary classification
at the node level.
So I just grabbed an example
of some very large graph,
but it could be millions of nodes.
And these are partially labeled.
So it's the same body as before
that we use for the graph classification.
And then we have vector outputs,
which are the same dimension
as the number of nodes.
If we just remove the mean pooling,
like in the node classification example,
we get the vector output one by n.
And then you can train
using binary cross entropy loss
on the nodes with the labels.
So the problem is that, at least here,
we're training,
let's say you have a graph
with millions of nodes,
that for the training
and that execution
at every layer of the network,
you have to read and process
every one
of the millions of nodes.
And so you could very easily
run into a situation
where you just don't have
the memory on your GPU
or the resource that you're using
to be able to store every node
on every layer of your network.
And then basically,
we're not doing batches here,
we can't do stochastic gradient descent.
So we're not taking advantage
of the fact
that randomly picking some of these nodes
and then running that.
But there are ways to do it.
And so three of the ways
there's others as well
is you can just randomly pick
a subset of the nodes as a batch
and run it
and then just pick
another subset
of the nodes.
And I'll explain what the issue
with that is
and then there's better ways,
something called neighborhood sampling
and graph partitioning,
which is better.
So the problem with just taking
a random subset,
so it's a small graph,
and let's say we're just picking a node
of one, size one, set one,
that this node, because of that aggregation,
it's dependent on the immediate neighbors
of that same node in the previous layer.
And in turn, each of these nodes
are influenced
by their immediate neighbors
of the previous node.
And so you can imagine
with a deeper graph,
and even if it's larger,
that you could quickly start basically
using up most of the network,
so actually using most of the network.
And just like in the convolutional
neural nets,
there's this notion
of receptive field.
So that growth, so the fact
that from the original input,
all of those nodes
are effectively
influencing this node,
you can call that the receptive field
for that particular node.
So, yeah, and the problem is
if you have fairly dense connections
and you have lots of layers,
you can quickly just expand
to encompass every node in the graph.
And so you haven't accomplished your goal
of having these distinct batches.
So the way neighborhood sampling works,
you have the, I guess,
a different graph here,
but the same random sampling
where you're just showing
all of the nodes
that influence this node here.
With neighborhood sampling,
you're doing the same thing,
but you're creating just a max,
a limit
to how many nodes
in your aggregation.
So you're saying like in this case,
I'm not going to use any more
than three of the neighboring nodes,
and you can just randomly
select
which three you use.
But that case, at least you bound the growth
as you go back into the network.
Does that make sense? Okay.
And there's a short notebook
that goes
into that a little bit more.
And then graph partitioning takes a graph,
and then what you do is you go
and you clip some of the edges,
and then you try to find these,
you know, using some algorithms,
you can find these kind of maximally
connected subsets of the graph
so that you partition them,
and then you basically just remove them,
and then you treat them as separate graphs.
And you can do that partitioning
on,
you know,
like every epoch,
you can change the partitioning
so that you cover some
of these
missing edges as well.
Okay.
Makes sense? Okay.
I'm not going to go into detail here.
It's in the book, but besides
the mean pooling,
there's a list in the book
on different ways that you can,
instead of just straight aggregation,
you can do things like enhance
the weight, the diagonal,
a little bit more in the equation up there.
You can add residual connections
just like we saw in the lecture
on ResNets.
You can just add
the previous hidden layer
to the output
of the activation function.
For the aggregation function,
you can weight them.
So you're taking an average
instead of a simple sum
on the aggregation.
This KIPF normalization is factoring in
that if you have a node
that's coming from,
that has a lot of neighbors,
maybe you don't want it
to overly influence
this aggregation here.
And so you can normalize it
a little bit there.
And then instead of you can do
a max pool aggregation.
Instead of summing,
you can just take
the max
of all the neighbors as well.
So just like with regular neural networks,
you can play with the different
kinds
of pooling operators.
Okay.
So then there is the analogy
to transformers.
You can also do aggregation by attention.
And essentially you're creating
a attention matrix,
or learning an attention matrix,
and then just kind of very similar
to transformers
is that so you're doing
a linear transformation on the input.
Remember when we took the input
and we transformed it
into the value vectors.
And then we had the query and the key.
There's not really a separate
query and the key,
but it is creating this attention matrix
and then multiplying by this linear transformed value.
So it is similar.
And so if you draw like we did before,
so this is the graph convolution
that I was just showing you
where you have the adjacency
matrix
which is fixed,
and then you have the input
which is going through a linear transformation,
and then you're just multiplying
by the adjacency matrix
or that plus the identity.
The graph attention, again,
it's not exactly like the transformers,
but it is now coming up
with these attention weights
and that's multiplying.
So it's this kind of hyper network
like I showed you for the transformers.
It is learning some attention weights
and then multiplying that
by the linear transformed input.
And just for comparison,
I put the, oops, text got cut off here a little bit,
but this was the regular dot product self-attention
where you had the query and the keys
and then you had the linear transform
and then it was being multiplied
by this attention matrix.
So not quite like the transformer,
but it does kind of integrate
some notions of the self-attention.
Okay? All right, we're actually
on the last topic here.
You guys are going to get out a bit early.
So edge graphs, so this
is actually quite simple.
You can take, let's say, some graph
that you have with the nodes.
You can create these, you know,
basically nodes corresponding to every edge.
So these are just labeled
by the nodes
that they connect, right?
So this is between nodes four and six,
so we just call it like four slash six.
So you can just add these at every edge
and then just remove all of the nodes.
And now you have, you know,
an edge graph, actually,
but this is representing, you know,
assuming now that we have
some useful information on the edges.
So we have edge embedding vectors.
We end up with what looked
like the node graph,
but it's just the edge
embedding vectors.
So everything that I just showed you before,
now you can just apply and do,
you know, whatever,
classification and regression on the,
with the node edge data.
So very, very simple to handle.
Okay? All right, it's a nice warm day,
so we can go enjoy the weather.
So next time my plan is to do
kind of a RLHF spin
on reinforcement learning.
So I'm not going to try to recreate
the other reinforcement class.
And then my plan is to talk about
this joint embedding predictive architecture
for the last class,
and then we'll have
the project presentations.
So like I said, I'll send out
a Piazza note tonight
with the assignment of who gets
which slot
on the 25th and the 30th.
And then I'll also, well, it's Tuesday.
We'll talk on Thursday,
but it's a good chance I'll be in office
for office hours this week as well.
Okay, thanks.
Thank you.