all right so
today we're
back on the
book chapter
I think
the treatment of Graphenolo networks was just fine
so actually follow it very closely
and it's more
I think straightforward
extension from
what we've been talking about
earlier as opposed to the
oops I forgot to move the
you are here pointer
but yeah a little bit more straightforward
extension from the neural net stuff
from the Gans and diffusion models and VAE
so
I think so I will keep
the final
report and repo
here I guess technically
I think Asama you're right because there's no final
you know they
they want me to start
doing grades after the last class but
it seems like it's not strictly enforced and so
this gives you some more time to clean things up
see why it's not
so
I only have two volunteers for the 25th
thank you to the both of you
so tonight I'm going to randomly select the other
6 I guess for
the 25th
and then everyone else will go on the on the 30th
and so
I'll let you know
the other thing is
I updated everyone see the final project info
I updated on the
website and grade scope so I put
a
little bit more instruction on the
video I updated the
report template the late lautech template
and
I put a comment a little bit more detail on the Github
repo so in the report
if you could put a link
to the repo and I think on grade scope I also
had it as well but the idea is that I mean like any
kind of well executed project
idea is to make it reproducible
and so somebody can come and reproduce your work
as the
kind of ideal case
any questions about final projects presentations
all right so let's jump in
so graph neural networks
I think this is an interesting space
not something that I had
really worked in before
but like I said it's a pretty straightforward extension
so the main challenge is that the topology of the graph
can vary the
types of connections in which are connected
which nodes are connected
the size of these graphs can be quite large
and we have to deal with a case where you have a single
monolithic graph which is
I'll show a bunch of examples but that's
pretty common case and so we'll talk about
what does it mean to do
batches of data and
because you need that force to cast the gradient
descent for example
so I'll cover
definitions we'll talk about representation
the so called adjacency matrix which is
crucial for describing the topology of the graph
and then get into the graph neural networks
how you build a convolutional layer
on top of a graph and then how you
how you build
graph
classification and regression at the graph level
and the node level
yeah I just realized that
I had also mentioned
we're gonna do a little recap of the
project maybe we'll push it to the Thursday
okay
all right so basic definition of examples so
generally so the
nodes sometimes they're called vertices
are connected by edges or links
you can have
undirected where there's no kind of implied
direction between the
the nodes or you can have directed
and if you do have a
directed connection if there's no cycles
nothing going back
upon itself then you can have a directed asyclic
graph and so sometimes you'll hear the term Dag
because there are certain things that you can do with
Dags
if they have those
two properties
so
we have been looking at we didn't really
treated as a graph per se but
you know we have been looking at
directed asyclic graphs
just the feed forward neural network is one example
right
but it's you know like it's kind of a regular
topology we didn't treat it as a graph
I also mentioned this in the VAE talk
these basean probableistic
graphical models that you can represent
something like this where you have like
a node that represents
a variable and so typically
you have something like a prior probability
with a directed edge to another variable
and then that node is representing the conditional
probability the
probability of that this takes on some value given some
latent variable in this case
so in the book there's
a bunch of examples as well
so road networks
are graphs where the
physical locations or the landmarks
are the nodes
the roads are the edges
chemical molecules are examples where the
nodes are atoms and the edges are
are chemical bonds between them
you can have electrical circuits as graphs
the nodes are components or the junctions
and then the edges are the wires connecting them
some other examples
so social networks
and this is where it can be very large
graphs you can take
like all of Facebook as a social network
the nodes are the people and the edges are
you know
people who have friended each other on the platform
scientific literature
the nodes are the papers
citations so these are directed
generally asyclic
where it's citing passwork and then there's
I'm not aware of actually much use
here
of something like a knowledge graph
but you can have this kind of hybrid
graph actually in this case yeah these are
all directed but there it is cyclic
actually in the book I think it says it's a cyclic
if I remember right but
I see one cycle right there
and actually
yeah
so
in this case you're trying to the edges correspond to
kind of relationships between entities that are the
nodes
so you can also things that are maybe not
you wouldn't typically think of as graphs but
if you have a 3d geometry
of a physical object like in this case of plane
the vertices in 3D
can be the nodes and then they could just
have connections to all
the nodes nearby
there's also there's a scene graph which
is can be used in 3d rendering but it's typically it's
uh describes the relationship of 3d objects
and these can be hierarchical
so you can have
in this case like a room description
where you have the connection between like
the back walls
connected to the right wall and the left wall
and the ceiling and the floor
then you have
a hierarchy so you can then have a
a lampshade which is broken further down
into components or you can have the table
which is broken further down
as well I put some links of papers that
some of them are applying neural networks to these
kinds of scene graphs
and then there's a bunch of other examples so Wikipedia
where articles are the nodes
and the hyperlinks are the edges
computer programs
you can
show as graphs in fact in the example that I did with
the Jupiter notebook for the micrograd
we were basically building a tensor compute graph
right if you remember
so
but yeah so proteins
can be the proteins are the nodes the edges
are where the proteins
interact and then
you can even have like sets or lists or even
images where you just have the six
or eight neighboring pixels
just connected to a particular pixel as well
okay
all right so
how do we describe these
typically we're going to define something called
like a node embedding
so we talked about embedding vectors with
transformers there's
actually some
analogies there which we'll see later but
you can have some kind of information that you have
basically translated into an embedding vector
for example typically they're all of the same dimension
you can also do the same thing with
edges so you can have
an edge embedding or embedding vector for every edge
and then typically
we'll define adjacency matrix
and the way you read this is that
this is just
in this case for undirected graphs
that you just read the indices
and so if there's a non zero
for example here at 3 comma 1
that means there's a connection between 3 and one
on the nodes and because
it's undirected
then you would expect
there's going to be a connection on one comma 3
so it's going to be symmetric
always asymmetric matrix
but the diagonal is typically zero because
there's no at least external edge connecting back to
itself
so you see the diagonals are zeros and then we have
non zeros actually
typically just put a 1
where there's a connection
and these can be
very sparse
and so sometimes you'll use sparse representation for
the matrices
okay so we could take
all of the node
data edges and then we can put them into a matrix
right so remember we have
a d dimensional embedding vector for every node
and we have let's say N nodes in this case
yeah it lines up 6 6 nodes
and so just like we were doing for transformers
you can put together
input matrix that is just
d dimension and then n columns 1 column for every node
and then the same thing for
the edges
you can have a different dimensionality to the
edges
but
they represent
each one of these edges and so there's probably
some kind of metadata here
but these are the connections that
they represent
okay so
let's look at
some properties of the adjacent C matrix
in this case this is a
simple undirected graph with eight nodes
and so you can
I guess the font's a little bit small but you can
convince yourself that
there's a one everywhere where there's a connection
on the graph
and so we can
describe one of the nodes as just a one hot and coated
vector right and so like node
is just a vector
the length this is
should be length 8
and then there's just
it's all zeros except the one at the 6 position
there right so
and then once you do that
you can
left multiply
the embedding vector
I mean the one hot vector here by the
adjacent C matrix
and what that gives you
just think about it right
you're taking each row and then you're multiplying here
so you're just pulling out the
whatever column is non zero in this case
you're just pulling out the six column
here and remember
on the adjacency matrix this is saying that
for the sixth node these are the nodes that
it's connected to right
and so
it's telling you that
these are just by
doing this multiplication
it's telling you those are the neighboring nodes
to the
node that we're interested in
and then you can do it again
you can left multiply
again by another a
adjacent C matrix
and now what is showing you
is that all of the nodes as you can reach in exactly
two steps
and you can
you can hit a node twice but you see like
is not
lit up is not colored
because
you can't get there in exactly two steps
it's not up to two steps it's exactly
two steps that it's describing
okay
and so
if you just multiply a by itself
what this is telling you
is that um
so I write it here
that yeah if you raise
a to you know whatever power
this was example of 2
just multiply by itself that many times
then
every position here
it contains the number of as it says here unique walks
of that length that you raise
the power to
the number of unique walks from node
n to
n so if you look here
let's say
1 2 3 4
1 2 3
well
okay that's probably
well yeah this is saying from four to four you can
there should be four unique walks
steps of two right is that
I don't see the fourth one
has anyone see the fourth one
oh it's 3 3 okay yeah
okay yeah and so
but the thing to remember here is that
this that value
that
it's not the number of unique paths
so you can visit the same node
but what you can think about is kind of an upper bound
so that means that there is some path
up to the value here
that with a connection
so there can be different distance walks between the
nodes
okay so now you can do
you can do some things like for example I just
created a tiny graph with
these node embeddings
these three dimensional node embeddings
which you can
put together into
a node data matrix
and then this should be the adjacency matrix for that
graph
you can define a permutation matrix
and the permutation matrix just has a 1
in each column and each row
so you can't have more than one 1 in a column or a row
but if you
take that data matrix and you write multiply it
you're basically just
permuting these right so
same thing again
you're just taking the rows and you're just grabbing
for each of these columns you're just grabbing
one of the columns out
and so
this permutation matrix here
is just permuting the
the values of the data matrix there
and
so you can do the same thing to the adjacency matrix
but you have to post multiply and
pre multiply by the transpose
and so you can
hopefully I did this right
so I permuted it I
left the old indices these are the new indices
I renumbered them of course they're just
different numbers but they still have the same
value there's the same topology they're just indexed
differently but
the new
adjacency matrix
should be correct for this
so
yeah let me talk about some properties
and then we'll go back to the kind of
permutation adjacent C matrix
so okay so
how do we extend this to a graph neural network
essentially
what we're going to do is we're going to take those
node embedding matrices
that I showed you
and the adjacency matrix
which describes the topology of the graph
and we're going to pass them through
layers of a neural network
so the note in beddings are updated at each
each layer so you have these kind of hidden
representation or hidden activations
after each layer
and of course when you start
the
input data is just the embedding vector of each node
but at the end
you have this this output which is
you have a representation for each node
but now it's incorporated context
from its neighbors in the rest of the graph
because as you'll see we're going to
kind of aggregate
information from the neighboring nodes
and so
yeah interestingly
this is kind of like word embeddings in a transformer
you know when you start out
you just have a unique word embedding
for every word or token
but as it travels through the transformer
that
what you have at the end is you have
you know kind of something that represents the word
in its context
to the other words in the sentence
okay so
you can do just like other neural networks
we can
create
classification and regression networks with these
and so
some examples for example you can give it a
molecular structure in graph form and then you can
try to figure out
if it's poisonous or not based on the chemical
structure or
you can regress boiling and freezing points so to
regression values out of a
molecular graph
yeah and so generally
just like with the other neural networks that we
that we saw that
you can put a head to the network right
so you can put a classification head
or a regression head at the end of the network
to get it into that kind of final
regression or classification form
and I'll show you some examples
so I'm going to start with just
the head
of the network and then I'll build up to how you build
the network itself but imagine you had
a graph with node embeddings
we're going to focus mostly
on node the node data at the very end
I'll show there's kind of a simple
way to handle
data in the edges as well the edge embeddings
but let's focus on the node embeddings first
so let's say you put it through some
neural network which we haven't defined
but you have on the output you're going to have some
activations or embeddings associated with each node
and then you can
combine it you can put it through a linear layer
and then you can put it through for example
a sigmoid or a Softmax or something like that
and then you can end up with probabilities for every
class
so here's an example for just binary
classification it's just kind of what
should look
pretty familiar you have the sigmoid
you have a beta a bias here
and then you have the weights and this one is just
a d dimensional row vector
and then you have
your embeddings matrix here
and so this is just multiplying every
it's just waiting every
column right of your embedding matrix
but then
in this case because we want to get a single output
we have this one
vector right this is just a
I think this is a
yeah
typo here this is just a column of ones right
and this has the effect of basically
summing
well because we're dividing by the number of vectors
this says the
basically just taking the average
of every one of those vectors
and so and collapsing it into
single value and so this is like
mean pulling like
we showed you before earlier
OK
okay and so that was at the graph level
so we collapsed everything into a single value
but you can also do it at the node level
so for example you can do binary
classification you can decide between let's say
one of two kinds of
nodes here and it's very similar
except you're
doing it on every embedding vector
this is not the matrix
the whole matrix of all the embedding vector stacked
this is just the individual node vector
indexed by the node number n
and then so you're doing that
now and you're producing a vector and then you have
actually this is a scaler
you're adding the bias
and then you're getting the value
just for that particular node
okay is that that makes sense
okay ah
yeah so here's an example where you can
decide let's say you have
in some cases maybe an edge doesn't exist
and you're trying to predict if a edge
should exist there
and so here
you can take the essentially the dot product
of the neighboring
node embedding vectors
send it through a sigmoid
and then you can train it to
basically give you the probability that
in fact this edge
should be there
just kind of another
example
okay
okay so
let's build up the
those were the heads of the graph let's build up
the body of the graph itself
just like we saw before when we were
seemed like a long time ago now
when we were building up
the deep neural networks
that you
know
we're just going to create all of these hidden layers
we're going to start with the input
we now have the adjacent C matrix
but we have parameters
for each layer
and then we're just going to have a bunch of
hidden layers
and then we're going
to end up with that final
hidden layer before we go to the head of the network
and so we're going to define what this function F is
to
create the next hidden layer
okay so just like in the convolutional
networks and some of the other
networks that we do care about
equivariants and invariants and so remember
equivariant means that if I
transform the input somehow
that the output is transformed the same way
so remember back to the permutation matrix
I can right multiply
my data matrix by the permutation and then I have to
left multiply and right multiply the adjacency matrix
but if I do that
then the output is just the
hidden
layer with the same permutation
right multiply by the same permutation matrix
and so so it's equivariant to the permutation
and then invariant
if we're doing something like sigmoid
since we're summing all of these up anyway
we don't really care if we're shuffling the
order of the nodes
and so in this case you know for doing like graph level
classification
it's invariant to permutation as well so
that's a valuable thing for the
for the graph neural networks
okay so let's now build out
a convolutional layer for the graph
and so
I'm going to define a function here the aggregation
function and essentially what it's doing
you can see here that for a particular node and a
particular
layer
k
that I'm just taking the neighborhood so n e
is just saying that
it's returning the indices of all the neighboring nodes
for the node not including itself
okay so
see how that's
going to be handy
and then the whole layer itself is we have a weight
matrix we're going to multiply it by
the node the embedding vector for the node itself
but we're also going to multiply it
against
the sum of all the neighbors
as well so it's kind of like the convolution right
we're taking weights and we're
waiting all of the neighborhood around
a pixel in that case
okay that makes sense
and we're using the same
the same weights for both
so there's already some weight sharing
happening here
and those
same weights are going to be applied to every node
in
that graph at that layer
just like in a convolutional network
okay so
um yeah so if you have in this case you have your input
you have after the first layer so you
do the aggregation for each node you have a
Omega 0 weight matrix
and then put it through an activation
and you get the first
hidden unit output the embeddings at each node
and then you can do this through
a bunch of layers until you get to the
last layer and then you just do it again
at the last layer
so
it should look a lot like
the regular neural nets
and the convolutional neural nets that you saw
okay so
so we have this
equation where we have the aggregates
we have this weight matrix
we applied it to the node embedding vector
and then also the
sum of all the neighbors
and then so if you do this to the
entire
you can do this to just the embedding vector of a node
but you can also just stack them all together
like the
data matrix that I was showing you
so Capital H here
and what you see is that you're applying it to the same
yeah so I guess the first thing that's
important to note here is that remember when we
write multiplied by the adjacent C matrix
we got all of the immediate neighbors of the node right
and so we're replacing
the aggregate function with this
right multiply by the adjacency matrix
and so now we have the
hidden layer
embedding matrix
showing up twice and so we can just factor it out
and then we have the
equation here and so you
can do it in matrix form on the whole data matrix
and then you just have the adjacency plus
this is the identity matrix here
so the nice thing is that
this is equivariant to permutations
it can handle an arbitrary number of neighbors
so that's all handled in the
adjacency matrix we don't have to
deal with any kind of weird indexing or anything
and it is you know the
adjacency matrix is describing the graph structure so
it can exploit any kind of graph structure
and then we are sharing parameters
across every one of the
notes so we have that kind of efficiency of
parameters as well
OK
okay so
let's put it all together now in
graph and node classification
and there are I'm going to release a few notebooks
they're pretty straightforward
but I think it's just it just helps to
have a little experience with the
with the Python code and the matrices
and the indexing a little bit
and so the one example you're going to see in the
Python notebook maybe it's yeah
13.2 notebook
is that
so you can put it all together
you can put a sigmoid
head on it like this with mean pulling
and then we can do
for example classification
and so in this case there's 118 elements
and so we can just have a 1 hot and coated
for every node to describe which element it is
and then the first parameter we can decide what
embedding dimension we want
so that first weight matrix here
can just be d by 118
so we switch to some d dimensional embedding
and then we have
the weight matrix which is a 1 by d row vector as well
but
with that you can put it all together
and now you basically have
a graph classification network for
I guess molecular compound detection
all right so
let me define
another term here so the stuff we've been talking about
up to date
with supervised learning
has been these inductive kind of models
and so
typically what we
do is we split our data into like training and test
data so we have separate data
we can hold out test and validation data
and then we can train on the
the training data and then test
on the testing data
but
with graphs you have this
case where you can have this transductive
kind of model
where you might have a case where you know
the labels of some of the nodes but you don't know
some of the
other nodes
but you can
do this kind of like semi supervised learning
is that you can still train
with this network
and
your loss function
is just incorporating your labeled nodes
and so at training time you're not taking into account
because we don't know the labels on these unknown nodes
but we can still proceed with training
but then at inference time
you could run inference on these
unlabeled nodes
okay
so that's the transductive
model
yeah so think about this example here where you have
you want to do
binary classification at the node level
so I just grabbed an example of some
very large graph
but it could be you know millions of nodes
and these are partially labeled
so it's the same body as before
that we use for the graph classification
and then we just
we have vector outputs which are the
same dimension as the
number of nodes
we just remove the mean pulling like in the
node classification example
we get the vector output
1 by n and then
you can train
using binary cross entropy loss
on the nodes with the labels
so
the problem is that at least here
were training let's say you have
a graph with millions of nodes
that for the training and that
execution at every layer of the network
you have to read and
process every
one of the millions of millions of nodes and so
you could very easily run
into a situation where you just don't have the
you know the memory on your
GPU or your you know the resource
that you're using
to be able to store every node on
every layer of your of your network
and then basically
you know we're not doing batches here
so you can't do stochastic gradient descent so
we're not taking advantage of the fact that
randomly picking some of these
nodes and then
running that but there are ways to do it
and so
three of the ways
there's others as well
we can just randomly pick a subset of the nodes
as a batch
and run it and then just pick another subset
of the nodes and I'll explain
what the issue with that is
and then there's better ways
something called neighborhood sampling
and graph partitioning
which
is better
so the problem with
just taking a random subset
and this is so it's a small graph
and let's say we're just picking
node of 1 size 1
reset 1
that this node
because of that aggregation
it's dependent on the immediate neighbors of
that same node in the previous layer
and in turn each of these nodes
are influenced by their immediate neighbors
of the previous note
and so you can imagine with
a deeper graph
and you know even if it's larger
with a deeper graph
that you could quickly
start basically
using up
most of the networks actually using most of the network
and just like in
the convolutional
neural nets there's this notion of receptive field
so that growth so the fact that
from the original input
all of those nodes are
effectively influencing this node
you can call that the receptive field for that
particular node
so yeah and the problem is
if you have fairly dense connections
and you have lots of layers
you can quickly just
expand to encompass every node in the graph and so you
haven't accomplished your goal of having these
distinct batches
so the way neighborhood sampling works so you have the
I guess a different graph here but the same
random sampling where you just
showing all of the nodes that influence this node here
with neighborhood sampling
you're doing the same thing but
you're creating
just
a max a limit to how many nodes in your aggregation
so you're saying like in this case
I'm not going to use any more than three
of the neighboring nodes
and you can like just randomly select
which three
you use but
that case at least you bound the growth as you go
back into the network
that makes sense
and there's a
short notebook that goes into that a little bit more
and then graph partitioning takes a graph and then
what you do is you go and you clip some of the edges
then you try to find these
using some algorithms
you can find these kind of maximally connected subsets
of the graph
so that you partition them
and then you basically just remove them
and then you treat them as separate
graphs and you can do that partitioning on
you know like every
epoch you can change the partitioning
so that you cover some of these missing
edges as well
okay
makes sense
okay I'm not going to go into detail here
it's in the book but besides the mean pulling
there's a list in the book on
different ways that you can
instead of just straight
aggregation you can do things like enhance the
weight the diagonal
a little bit more in the equation up there
you can add residual connections just like we saw in
the
lecture on resonance you can just add the previous
hidden layer
to the
output of the activation function
for the aggregation function you
can weight them
so you're taking an average
instead of a simple sum on the aggregation
this Kip normalization
is factoring in that
if you have a node that's coming from
that has a lot of neighbors maybe you
don't want it to overly influence
this aggregation
here so you can you can normalize it a little bit there
and then instead of
you can do max pool aggregation instead of summing
you can just take the max of
all the neighbors as well
so just like with
regular neural networks
you can play with
the different kinds of pooling operators
okay so
then there is the analogy to transformers
you can also do aggregation by attention
and
essentially you're creating a
attention matrix
are learning and attention matrix
and then just
kind of very similar to transformers
is that
so you're doing a linear transformation on the input
remember when we took the input
and we transformed it into the value vectors
and then we had the query in the key
there's not really a separate query in the key
but it is creating this attention matrix
and then multiplying by this linear transformed
value
so it is similar
and so if you if you draw like we did before
so this is the the graph convolution
that I was just showing you where you have the
adjacency matrix
which is fixed
and then you have the input
which is going through a linear transformation
and then you are multiplying by the
adjacency matrix or the
that plus the identity the graph attention again
it's not exactly like the Transformers but it is now
coming up with these attention weights
and that's multiplying
so it's this kind of hypernetwork
like I showed you for the Transformers
it is learning some
attention weights
and then multiplying that
by the linear transformed input
okay and just for comparison I put the
text got cut off here a little bit but
this was the regular dot product self attention
where you had
the query
and the keys and then you had the linear transform
and then it was
being multiplied by this attention tension matrix
so not quite like
the transformer but it
does integrate some notions of the
the trans the self attention
okay
all right we're actually on the last
topic here you guys are going to get out a bit early
so edge graphs so this is actually quite simple
you have the
take let's say
some graph that you have with the the nodes
you can create these
you know basically nodes
corresponding to every edge
so these are just labeled by
the nodes that
they connect right so this is between nodes 4 and 6
so we just call it like 4 slash 6
so you can just add these
at every edge
and then just remove all of the nodes
and now you have a
you know an edge graph actually
but this is representing
you know assuming now that we have
some useful information on the edges
we have edge embedding vectors
we end up with what looked like the node graph
but it's just the
edge embedding vectors so everything
that I just showed you before
now you can just apply
and do
you know whatever classification or regression on the
with a node edge data
so
very very simple to handle
okay
all right it's a nice warm day so we can
go enjoy the weather
so next time my plan is to
do kind of a
RL HF spin on reinforcement learning
so I'm not going to try to recreate the
the other reinforcement classing class
um and then
my plan is to talk about these
joint embedding predictive architecture for the
last class
and then we'll have the project presentations
so like I said I'll send out a Piazza note tonight
with the
assignment of who gets which slot on the 25th and the
30th but and then also
what's Tuesday
I will talk on Thursday but it's a good chance I'll be
in office for office hours this week as well
okay thanks