OK,
so I want to talk
about diffusion models.
So this is,
I guess,
rounding out the generative image parts.
I know there was,
when I sent out
the survey at the beginning of the class,
I know there was interest
on generative AI.
Actually,
I'm not sure if it was mainly just the LLM stuff,
which we covered,
or also the vision stuff.
But so for diffusion models,
as I alluded
to last time,
so you're not going
to get through all of the details of how diffusion models work.
It's just very math - heavy,
ideally.
I mean,
I can imagine
a short course just on generative image models.
And diffusion models,
there's so much going on.
So what I hope to do last time
is at least give you a sense,
build some intuition about what's going on.
And you'll have to dive in.
And actually,
if anyone's interested,
happy to do a little side project with you if you want.
I can always create
more content as well.
So also,
like last time,
the book,
at least the way the book organized things,
I didn't find it that accessible.
And so I'm going to rely
heavily on a similar blog from last time.
And I guess this might be publicly available.
I realize I referenced towards data science
because I subscribe.
If you don't have access,
and I'm pointing to something that you don't have access,
just let me know.
I can do like a print
screen or something of the site
and share it.
Oh,
and then in terms of announcements,
so did Xavier reach out to,
last time I mentioned,
you're nodding
your head,
yeah,
so what I asked him to do is take the five people
on the top of the leaderboard.
So am I remembering
right?
It's like Andy,
Jessica,
Fareed,
Jasmine,
who else?
And you're as well.
Yeah,
and so what I asked
Xavier is just organize,
just collect amongst you just what your training tactic was
and what model you use.
And then he'll put it together in a slide
if there's not a huge difference.
But let's spend
at least a few minutes,
10 minutes,
or something at the beginning of next class on Tuesday.
That would be interesting.
We can learn something
about your approaches.
And congrats
for being top of the leaderboard too.
And I think that's it for announcements.
OK,
so I'm going to try to give some context about how diffusion models
work
and then go into a little bit of the theory.
But I'm not going
to go into all of the math.
It's just not conducive to try to do it
in a lecture
format.
And I forget who said it,
but math is not a spectator
sport.
And so I encourage you to go in and actually just kind of re - derive
either what's in the book
or in this blog post here.
Because even here,
they skip some steps
and I'll certainly skip some steps here.
And then I'll talk
a little bit about how you get to training
and then flash some application examples.
OK,
so kind of like last time,
the idea is that we're going to somehow figure out a probability
distribution.
And we're going to try to generate new samples
from that probability distribution
and the new samples will be hopefully high quality images.
So the way diffusion models
work
is that they essentially start kind of like with the variation
al auto encoders and also GANs.
And I'll make the comparison
here in a little bit.
But like in the Wendy example,
it starts with just random noise.
And basically what you've done is you learned
a generative model that can go from a purely Gaussian random distribution
to some more complicated distribution that reflects the data set of images in this case.
So it's the exact same thing
for images.
It's just that it's a much higher dimensional space.
But basically every color of every pixel,
you have a multidimensional distribution across that.
So we're going to try,
and just probably like last time,
it seems counterintuitive,
we're going to start from noise and somehow we're going to generate
these high quality images.
So what's interesting,
so I lectured in the slightly reversed order.
But these three key papers
came out for each of these three areas just a year apart.
So in 2013,
King Ma and Welling introduced the variational auto encoder,
which I talked about.
2014,
Goodfellow and others introduced GANs.
And then 2015,
Saul Dijkstein introduced this paper.
It's called
Deep Unsupervised Learning Using Non - Equilibrium Thermodynamics.
So it wasn't clear
from the paper title
that these became the diffusion models.
And there have been variations
of that since then.
And of course,
there's a lot of commercial,
so a lot of excitement,
especially after these more efficient versions,
like stable diffusion,
which I'm not going to really go into.
I'll mention
very briefly at the end.
But of course,
Dali 2,
Dali 3,
Imogen from Google,
Make a Scene from Meta,
Imagine Video,
so going into video space from Google
and Make a Video from Meta,
Stable Diffusion 3,
just came out from Stability AI.
And then there's Mid Journey that they're on.
Now they're model version 6.
And you've seen examples.
I'll show some today as well.
But this is from Meta's Make a Scene
that's generating
images from a sketch and a text prompt.
They don't show the input here.
But the idea is that you have a lot of creative control now.
You can sketch and not just verbally describe what's going on.
OK,
so what's the basic idea
of these diffusion models?
Or they call
them
diffusion probabilistic models.
So the idea is you take this,
and I'll describe what this stochastic process is,
but there's a forward process
that you take in your training.
You take
all of these high quality images.
And you slowly add noise to them,
where you get to essentially a fully random image.
But you have all of these samples.
And then the goal of diffusion models is you're trying
to learn the reverse process.
You're basically trying to figure out,
from a random sample,
can I get back to one step at a time,
can I get back to some high quality image?
And if there's no other information,
it'll just come back to something
that's high quality.
But there's these conditional diffusion models,
just like the conditional GANs and VAEs,
that you can give it
text prompts,
or as we saw in the other one,
give it even image
input
to kind of guide how it does this reverse diffusion process.
And OK,
so we're going to hopefully give you some intuition about how this works.
And so I'll start by,
I'll talk
about what are stochastic processes,
and specifically
diffusion processes,
then give a little bit
of intuition,
hopefully,
behind these diffusion probabilistic models.
I'm going
to go into a little bit of math.
Not going
to do the complete derivation,
like I said,
and then talk about how it's trained in practice.
All right?
OK,
so let's just to kind of set things
up a little bit.
When we're talking
about stochastic processes or diffusion processes,
we're talking
about random variables.
And what makes a random variable a stochastic process
is that you basically have continuously varying
random variable in the continuous case,
index by time,
or you can have discrete random variables that are just indexed either by indexing points of times
or just simple indexing.
And so when you have a random variable
and you have a realization
of it,
that's what we call it,
a sample.
You have one example
or one sample from the random variable.
But for the stochastic process,
a realization
is a sample path.
So over time,
how did that random variable kind of evolve over time?
Let me show you some pictures.
So there are,
like I said,
there are discrete time and continuous time
random variables.
But there's also discrete value
and continuous value.
So discrete time,
let's say you're taking
daily average temperature.
Once a day,
you're recording
an average temperature
or coin flipping discrete events.
Whereas continuous time,
you're monitoring
the,
I guess,
the second - by - second stock price values.
Or you're monitoring
queue length,
which can change instantaneously.
But presumably,
it's like queue of people.
It changes
by discrete value.
So the temperatures are,
to some precision,
are basically continuous value.
It's the same to stock price.
But coin flip,
of course,
is discrete value.
And queue length,
if you're counting the number
of people
or the number of jobs in your
batch queue on the
SCC,
then they're going
to be discrete values.
But the queue size can change,
basically,
instantaneously at any point in time.
So we're going to use the properties
of a Markov process.
And a Markov process is basically,
it's a stochastic process,
but as it says with no memory.
So that just means that the current value at the current time is only dependent
on the previous value.
So if it wasn't Markov process,
then it can be dependent
on all the previous values
or realizations of the process.
But with Markov,
basically,
everything you need to know to figure out what's coming
next is in the last sample.
OK,
and so a diffusion process now is,
so it can be described
by a stochastic differential equation.
So differential equation is just something that's referring
like some infinitesimal change of some value,
usually versus some other
variable,
like time.
But a stochastic differential process
has a random process inserted as well.
And so this is kind
of the standard form,
is here's our variable that we're trying
to predict
or measure.
You have this thing called
the drift coefficient,
which is deterministic,
but it can be dependent
on the value of your random variable
and the point in time.
So it can be varying
in a deterministic way.
And then you have something
called a diffusion coefficient
,
which can be dependent
on the value of the random variable
and the time.
And then it's the
product
with a so - called Wiener process
that I'll describe here in a minute.
And I'll show some pictures.
And again,
just to emphasize,
so the drift coefficient
and the diffusion coefficient are functions
of the value of the random variable
and time.
OK,
so as I said,
this part here,
if you just mask out this,
this is just a regular differential equation,
but this makes it
a stochastic differential equation.
OK,
so let's talk
about what a Wiener process is.
So it's a continuous time
stochastic process that has these properties.
Generally,
just by convention,
the first sample is 0,
kind of doesn't really matter where it starts.
But it has independent
increments.
And so it has this
Markov property
that any two samples that are side by side
are independent of all the past samples.
And then probably the key thing
to take away here is that the difference,
and so if I take,
even in the continuous case,
if I take two samples
and I take the difference,
they're going to be normally distributed with mean of 0.
So I have
this Wiener process or Brownian motion process.
I take a sample.
Doesn't matter even when.
I take another sample,
some later point.
That difference is going to be followed this
Gaussian distribution with 0 mean.
And the
variance
is just related to the distance between the samples.
I mean,
think about it.
So here's a picture
right here.
These are just different
Wiener processes that start 0.
And because of the random nature,
of course,
they'll have different paths.
And so you can calculate
the standard deviation,
which is just related
to the distance from the first sample,
which is the gray area here.
And so it kind of makes sense.
If it's randomly
jumping up and down
in this 1D case,
the further away you get,
the more likely you are to be farther from 0.
So it kind of makes sense.
Yep?
Is the curve
generated differentiable everywhere?
Or is it not differentiable
anywhere?
It's kind of jagged?
Yeah.
We are going
to be differentiating.
But we're going
to be differentiating the equations,
I guess,
for the curve.
But I think what you're asking is,
can you differentiate
the kind of the realizations?
I mean,
because you're referring
to the jagged nature.
So I guess short answer is yes,
from an analytical perspective.
So you'll see we'll have an expression
for this stochastic differential equation.
And we will be differentiating,
because we're going
to build that into our loss function of a network that we're going to be training.
Makes sense?
OK.
So I do like my profiles.
So I threw one in here.
So the
Wiener process is named after Norbert Wiener.
He's an interesting
character.
He was at MIT.
He's kind
of a child prodigy.
But he was a computer scientist,
and he died in
64,
but in the early days.
But he was credited with creating,
at the time,
it was called the field of cybernetics.
So he did a lot
of research around these kind of stochastic processes and these noise processes.
And basically,
they became key contributions
to areas in electrical engineering,
communication,
control systems, like Wiener filter,
if you've ever looked at control.
And actually,
we use it sometimes in computer vision.
And so he was kind
of a contemporary or slightly older,
but he influenced,
like,
John von Neumann,
who,
you know,
famous mathematician and was credited
with kind of inventing the modern computer architecture, the CPU
kind of architecture.
It's still called the von Neumann architecture
today. Claude
Shannon,
who's the basically creator of information
theory or information science.
And so he,
you know,
interesting enough,
he wrote a,
I put a link here,
he wrote a paper in 1949
called The Machine Age,
you know,
again,
think back to 1949,
but anticipating,
you know,
a lot of what's happening
today
around robots and things like that.
And there was a,
I don't know,
if you're interested,
there's an interesting book,
I guess it's kind
of niche,
but where they call him
the Dark Hero of the Information Age,
I found it interesting.
And then the other little tidbit is that he's my great,
great grand advisor.
So if you do
your academic genealogy,
I'm one of the PhD students,
probably know what I'm talking
about,
that,
so my advisor was at MIT.
His advisor,
Oppenheim and Schaefer, they kind of founded the field of digital signal processing,
which I did my PhD in.
And actually,
interesting enough,
their advisor was Amar Bose
, founder of Bose Corporation,
and Bose was a student
of Norbert Wiener.
So a little bit
of trivia.
So I feel compelled to understand what he's done.
I'm not sure I'm doing it justice,
but.
Okay,
so let's go back.
So we have these,
just look at
the,
think about the Wiener process itself.
We can take those samples,
like a sample that's just some small time apart from another sample.
And as I showed you on the other,
on the previous slide,
that that difference is always going to be a zero mean,
and the standard deviation is always going to be the,
basically,
the distance between the samples.
So if you take samples
further apart,
it's going
to have bigger standard deviation.
That makes sense.
Okay,
so we can discretize
that stochastic differential equation by just taking two samples and subtracting them from each other.
And that basically,
so there's a little bit
of assumptions here,
which I didn't make explicit.
But I think they're assuming
that these are kind of slow moving.
So these are,
this is an approximation.
These are slow moving curves.
And so they're not taking account that these values might have,
might have changed.
But it's just factoring in the difference
of the Wiener process here.
And so it went from this,
the Wiener process
to this,
this zero mean Gaussian.
Okay,
by taking
the,
taking the difference.
And then we can just bring this term over here.
And then if you have,
so if you have a zero mean Gaussian and you're multiplying
it by some value,
you're just changing,
you're just creating
a new Gaussian.
Right,
and so u becomes u,
u prime.
We're,
we're multiplying
it by something.
So this is now just a Gaussian,
zero mean.
But the standard
deviation is just the constant,
you know,
or the value that's being multiplied here.
Okay,
does that make,
make sense?
Okay,
so let's look at actually going
back to the stochastic differential equation.
There's different,
different flavors of the equation plotted here.
This line
in the middle,
this dashed line
is just basically a constant.
It's just saying that,
just for reference,
it's just saying that nothing changes,
it's actually not.
These are,
these are kind of the dashed lines are these non,
non stochastic equations just for reference.
But if I have no deterministic part
and I just have
the Wiener process,
then just like before,
it's just going
to kind of wander around starting from the,
the zero mean,
right?
That's the,
the equation at the, at the top.
This one is,
this is a simple differential equation,
this dashed line here,
dx equals 2 dt,
that the,
the coefficient is,
is just a,
a constant,
right?
The,
the drift coefficient
is just a constant.
So,
and then here,
you see that,
so you have this,
it's just kind of growing,
you know,
linearly with,
with time,
and then you're,
you're adding the,
the Wiener process on,
on top of it.
And then the,
the line down here,
now it's getting,
you know,
a little bit more,
you have the,
the drift coefficient
is a simple function
of the random variable itself,
and you have something,
some non unitary drift coefficient
as well for the,
the purple,
purple line here.
And so,
you can see that the standard deviation because we have a bigger constant,
multiplying the, the Wiener process,
it's kind
of wandering around quite a bit,
quite a bit more.
Okay,
all right,
so we,
we want to reverse this,
this process,
and so we had the,
the stochastic differential equation,
and so here's where I'm going to start skipping a bunch
of math,
but you know,
can encourage you to,
to do it,
or we can talk offline,
is that we can just define this new
variable
x hat,
which is just instead of starting
from time zero
and going to like time capital T,
it's x hat,
we just define it to be capital T minus T,
right?
So if you have,
basically when we're,
we're going to be talking
a lot about time here,
so probably can point to this that the normal diffusion process like I was showing
is going
from zero to time
T,
and now x hat,
x hat is going,
going back that way.
So with some manipulations
and some substitutions,
you can write what looks like,
actually there,
there's one thing that's also a little bit
different here,
is that the diffusion coefficient is only dependent
on time,
it's not dependent
on the random variable value itself,
but with that assumption,
you can write,
you can rewrite the equation and then basically get it in a form,
you know,
substituting these variables, it looks very much like just another stochastic differential equation.
Okay.
And this,
this term here has a special name,
the gradient of log
of the probability distribution of the
random variable,
it's called
the,
the score function,
whereas the probability
of the random variable
is just the,
the marginal probability.
Okay.
So it turns out that if you have this,
this kind of stochastic differential equation,
that if you carefully pick your,
your drift coefficient
, your diffusion coefficient,
that you can start with,
you know,
any kind of distribution over here.
And basically,
you can guarantee that if you take enough steps that you will end up at some point with a,
just a pure Gaussian distribution.
So you're,
this is,
so it's an equation that,
you know,
essentially diffuses the,
your complicated distribution to a simple Gaussian distribution.
And,
and this is the form of the equations that will be used in the diffusion modeling.
I warned you guys,
it can be a lot of,
a lot of math,
right?
Okay.
So let's develop
a little bit more intuition.
So we had this,
this form like I,
I showed you here and that,
so if you,
you pick it,
the values of this form
and
p
is between zero and one,
you know,
you'll have this,
this property.
And you can take,
you know,
step by step,
you can substitute
for every subsequent step.
Like for example,
at the final step over here,
of course,
the equation is simply just the previous step.
And then you just keep going back another step
and substitute back in there
and then when you do all of that,
you end up with a equation like this,
which is kind
of of the same form.
You have the,
your first sample value over here,
and then you just have these,
this kind of sum of like the,
the square root of square root of one minus p
raised to the ith power of the summation.
But they're all just multiplying
one of these Gaussian, these normal distribution random variables.
And so when you're,
of course,
when you're multiplying
something like a normally distributed random variable
or something,
all you're doing is you're just changing the,
the variance of that random variable.
So you can view this as simply
just a sum of independent Gaussians,
which you can then just add up
all the standard deviations to get just a single, single Gaussian.
Okay,
so if you do that for large enough step sizes,
then the,
the value here as T goes in Finnish, as T goes in Finnish,
eventually going to go to zero.
And this is just a geometric
series here.
If you're looking at
the,
the variance,
so you,
you square the terms inside here
as T goes to infinity, that this just collapses into this closed form representation from the geometric series.
And as T goes
in Finnish,
this just becomes one.
And so this,
this tells you that,
again,
this diffusion process works analytically.
You take enough steps,
you're eventually going to get to just a unit
standard Gaussian.
Okay,
and that,
and that's what we're doing,
but with for images.
Okay,
you start here with a picture,
actually it already looks a little noisy picture of a cat.
And then you're just adding,
adding noise to the point where,
you know,
at some point you basically just have
a Gaussian random noise distributed image.
And for every step,
it's just that equation that I,
that I showed you.
So actually the forward pass,
you don't have to learn anything.
You can just use this,
this process is that you're,
you're adding noise
in this kind of structured,
structured way,
step by step.
Okay,
so the question is,
so why,
why use this seemingly complicated process?
So it turns out that,
you know,
gives us this kind of structured way of going step by step to go from any complex distribution
to a standard normal distribution.
And it does it in a way,
and hopefully I'll show you enough to convince you that it does it in a way that you can learn
the reverse process.
And generally,
it's really easy to go from a original image
to just a pure noise image,
right?
You can just go through that process,
but it is,
you know,
it's hard to go,
go the other way.
But,
you know,
if you think about it,
you do get some,
some clues.
Like maybe this first step is difficult when you just have pure noise,
but,
you know,
maybe you're getting something
that looks like a image,
but those clues
kind of influence what happens,
you know,
now it's maybe just a little bit easier because,
you're starting
to get to,
you know,
some sample in your space,
and then it,
you know,
generally can get easier as you progress.
And in fact,
that's kind of key to this,
so you can write it in a closed form like that,
the forward pass,
which is not trained,
you just apply
that equation,
you know,
you can just take the composition
of all those functions,
and you could write a big function,
you know,
that tries to go from random noise to your,
final image,
but it's a really hard,
you know,
probably impossible thing to do.
First of all,
it can be very large function,
but it's also probably doesn't behave
well from a kind of a gradient perspective,
you kind of have like one shot to try to learn this model,
whereas when you do it in this
step by step,
each of these mappings here,
what usually happens is this is learning kind of a course step first,
and then as the image gets better,
it's learning
kind of finer and finer updates to get to the final image,
that seems to be helping,
and it also turns out
that the nature of this function can be the same,
it's just a,
actually I'll show you,
it can be just like a UNET or a transformer model,
and so you're just adapting,
there's some parameterization,
you know,
like just the time step that's changing,
and so you can actually reuse weights,
you know,
learn a function
G
that takes as the image as its input,
the noisy image,
and the time step,
and it's that same model
with just different inputs
and different time steps,
and so it turns out
to be much more efficient
just in terms of the number of parameters and the size of the model.
So,
and that's basically what it's saying here.
and you know,
for these multi - step process
just the gradient descent is better behaved.
Okay.
Yeah,
this is the point I just made before,
is that we can have the exact same,
so now these aren't different transforms,
these are exact same transforms,
and they're just,
the arguments to them are just the image that's going in
and which step that we're on,
so we can reuse the process.
So,
in a lot of ways,
it's similar to variational auto encoders with some key differences,
so it is,
it's going from the encoder or the diffusion,
forward diffusion,
is going from a complex distribution
to a simple,
so like the encoder in the VAE,
and it's learning
decoder to go in the other direction to produce a sample that looks like something from your sample set,
but as I mentioned that this,
unlike VAE,
this is a multi - step process,
the encoder is fixed,
so we're not actually learning the encoder like in VAE,
and we're using this diffusion process to train.
The other big thing is that in VAE,
remember we were shrinking the latent space was a smaller dimension,
but it's key here that the model
at each step
has exact same size input as it has output,
okay?
All right,
so I'm just gonna get a little bit deeper,
I'm not gonna go through all the math.
Anyone see
the problem with the,
what is it,
what do you see?
Yeah,
so it's still,
again,
doing a lot better with words,
but not perfect.
Okay,
but again,
I'm not gonna go through all of the math here,
but,
all right,
so let's,
so we're gonna assume that we're gonna operate
in T discrete steps,
and we're gonna assume that these are Markov processes,
and so they only depend
on the step before in the, in either direction.
And so we can define the so - called transition probability that basically says,
okay,
at a current time stamp,
current sample,
there's a distribution,
this conditional distribution is saying that given,
if I take
a new sample given the previous sample,
that it's going
to be a normal distribution,
and this is reminiscent
of that equation that I showed you,
right?
Because it's just going to be,
the mean is going to be centered
around your last sample
with that weighting that I showed you in that previous equation, and the variance,
we're just multiplying
that,
the previous value by some value
beta,
and so that's gonna influence
the variance or standard deviation.
And this gives us some,
a way to do a trade - off
between basically how much information to keep from the previous sample.
Yeah,
and so we can,
for this next sample,
we can say,
because this is the trick,
we use,
I guess a number
of times now with these Gaussian random variables,
is that if you take
the previous
random variable at t minus one,
you multiply it by something,
or actually,
this is a deterministic value.
If you take the,
some random process,
and you multiply it by something,
you're just changing the standard
deviation and shifting it.
So this is equivalent
to this up here,
right?
We're just shifting it
and changing the
standard
deviation.
Okay,
so we can go all the way
from step zero to step T
in kind of this closed form,
but it just becomes
the product of all of those equations.
And so you have essentially those,
the one minus betas that were here,
this is just previous step.
We can just multiply all those out,
right?
And then you have the product of those terms,
So if you want to go figure out the probability
over all the steps,
you just multiply the each step,
that going back,
right?
So it turns out
that with the choices of the drift
and the diffusion coefficients,
that you can write the transition probability
the probability of the previous sample.
So now we're going back the other way.
You can write
it
in a kind of very similar way.
So now this is the kind of the important direction because we have to figure out,
we have to learn this.
We want to denoise,
go back this way.
And so we can write in this form,
but it's going to be based on some function that's going to determine the mean
and some function that's going to determine
the covariance.
And we don't know what those are yet,
but let's assume that they're parameterized,
but they're basically,
we can use deep learning models
to do that.
Okay,
so you can do the same thing
now in the reverse direction.
If you're trying
to do over the whole sequence,
it's just a product of all of those conditionals,
right?
Going back.
And yeah,
just the starting term here was not dependent
on time.
It's just a regular Gaussian.
Okay,
so with a little leap of faith here,
we have the function
going forward.
This forward process,
which is,
we don't have to learn it.
It's just defined here.
And now we have this reverse process.
And at least we have a description
for the probability distribution,
but it's based on some parameters here that we have to learn.
So,
yeah,
so the question is,
how do we learn those parameters?
And we're going to,
we wanna train a deep learning model,
so how do we
define
the loss function?
So,
remember,
we had a,
we defined
a,
or you can think of a probability
distribution when you're training,
you have these example,
your dataset.
So you have a probability
distribution of the original model.
And then you're going all the way
to the noise.
And then when you come back,
we have this probability
distribution of our denoising process.
And the goal is to make this look like this,
right?
So we want the result of our denoising,
the probability
distribution,
we want it to look like the distribution of our
dataset,
of our sample set,
right?
And so,
how do we compare probability
distributions?
What's the measure,
yeah?
KL divergence.
KL divergence,
yeah,
yeah.
And so,
similar to like in the VAE,
we're going
to build a loss function that is going to try to find the models
the parameterized models for the mean
and the variance.
So that the divergence
from the actual distribution to the learned denoised distribution is minimized.
And this is where I'm going to wave my,
wave my hands.
I'm going to skip a lot more math,
you can thank me.
But,
you know,
if you go through,
there's a bunch
of tricks.
And again,
suggest you try this
if you're interested,
but I just captured
some of the tricks here.
Expanding the probability
sub theta,
use Jensen's inequality.
And so the equation
for that divergence,
you can use Jensen's inequality to find a upper bound.
That's simpler.
And so if you minimize the upper bound,
simpler equation,
you're minimizing
the actual equation.
So the book also talks
about this as well.
There's some manipulations with
Bayes theorem.
There,
you can take advantage
of the properties that the
KL
divergence, that both of these are Gaussian distributions.
And so you can,
there's some properties of
KL
divergence measures
of two Gaussians that you,
you can use.
And then there's actually another simplification suggested
by Ho et al
in this paper of 2020.
That simplified it even more.
Just kind of,
I guess,
I don't know if he guessed,
but it's not analytically derived,
but it turns out that it actually works even a little bit
better than the analytical derivation.
And so the forward process again,
was what I showed you,
this reverse process where we have to learn these parameters.
And then this kind
of the near final,
it's like the simplified,
it was the upper bound with Jensen's inequality,
and then this other step.
But it's basically,
what's kind of interesting here,
is what is trying to do it every step,
is trying to minimize the noise measures
of the sample that's coming in,
and the noise that you're producing.
Okay,
so we can leave the math for the most part.
so it's very involved,
how to get in the training process,
but I'm gonna summarize
it at a high level.
So again,
maybe you got some intuition.
And I did ask Xavier,
I didn't find a good small example.
I think he showed some of
VAE and GAN example,
right?
Anyone go to the discussion
section?
Yeah,
so I asked him to do a diffusion example for next week.
We'll see if you can find a good,
simple example.
But the idea is basically this.
And so this is the training process.
So you start
with a sample image,
and you have noise,
and basically you generate a random step
by adding the
image,
the noise to the image.
And then you try to take a guess at what the image would look like from this noisy image,
from through this parameterized model.
And from that,
you're estimating
the noise of the noisy image.
And then for the gradient
descent step,
you have the estimated noise and a measure
of the true noise.
And you calculate
gradient descent,
which I didn't cover.
It's kind
of more involved,
but you can update the model parameters when you do that.
And there's some pseudo code there at the top,
kind of saying the similar thing.
So when you sample it after you've trained,
the process is like this.
So you start step one,
so you just start
with pure random noise.
You're estimating,
so you're using this model that you've learned to estimate
the noise of the current state.
You take a first best guess of some image that's not gonna look very good.
And then you do a linear combination
between the current state
and the estimated noise from the original sample
to create a new sample.
And basically you just,
you keep doing that through that transform.
And then you'll progressively
get better.
That's the pseudo code for it.
But so the model you can use,
just you can just use the good old
UNET,
the old encoder decoder architecture with some kind of time embedding.
UNET is nice
because you have the exact same resolution
of your input to your output,
right?
That's one of the requirements.
I think this is literally the size
of the model.
The thing that's,
not sure when it was added,
but there is these residual blocks,
the normal residual blocks from UNET,
right?
So you,
these are convolutional layers,
and then you have these residual connections
that get added in when you're doing the deconvolution side.
But they also added these residual blocks
with self - attention,
so kind of interesting.
So taking a little bit
from the transformer architecture and putting a self - attention head.
And I don't know,
I have to check,
or you guys can check,
like how many,
if it's multi - headed attention
or not.
But that's,
you know,
the complicated part was,
or is deriving the loss function.
You know,
once you have the
loss function,
the model architecture itself is not complicated.
And yeah,
so basically you train that model.
It has the time step that's coming in,
but you're just running that model at every step.
This is actually the reverse process,
even though it's going to the right.
And there's,
but you can imagine,
there's just been
a ton of innovation and experimentation here.
I'll show you a couple of examples,
but they,
you know,
trying lots of even transformer base.
Yeah.
Sorry,
I can't see that the difference
between the heat of the rocks.
Down here?
Yeah,
it's the exact same model.
There's nothing changing.
It's getting
the time index coming in.
So it has the,
of course,
different input.
And then I think it's kind of showing it here.
There's a time embedding that's incorporated
as well.
And I'm not exactly sure
offhand how,
but is that your question?
What exactly does text come in?
Yeah,
so text is conditional generation.
So the,
yeah.
So indeed,
it didn't incorporate any kind of external additional prompting.
And so there's,
of course,
a lot of variants here,
but I call out two of them.
Is there's classifier guidance like I showed on the,
was it the VAE or GAN lecture
now,
but where you're incorporating
class information
and you're influencing the reconstruction based on class,
and I'll show you a picture
example,
or guidance from text.
And basically what you're doing is you're incorporating,
you're using a language model,
like a transformer,
to create an embedding.
And then you're adding that,
you're injecting
that into the flow.
And I have a,
I think I have a picture here.
But,
and then there's other examples,
like I mentioned at the very beginning,
that you can also show it a sketch and text.
So there's variations
here.
But here's,
this is this paper by Dari Wal and Nickel,
that's doing,
again,
it's ImageNet,
and is just taking the ImageNet class as guidance here.
And so you can imagine that it didn't put the labels here.
This is an example from the book,
but you can kind of guess what the class labels are,
and it's doing,
you know,
high quality generation.
So,
but yeah,
so for text,
this is one example.
This is Saharia,
and I guess pretty recent,
2022,
but this is taking a language model,
but it's also doing this
hierarchical,
this kind of cascaded.
So it does low resolution,
and then that feeds into a slightly higher resolution,
and then that feeds into a slightly higher resolution as well.
But you see the embedding vectors are injected,
and I don't know offhand the exact architecture,
but you can imagine that it's being added
at some of the layers.
I mean,
for UNET,
it's probably
being remapped into two - dimensional kind of feature vector,
so that it can be added in,
or it could be,
you know,
weighted across channels or something.
You have to look at the paper to see exactly how.
But of course,
yeah,
so lots of examples now.
This was again from the Saharia paper,
but and I guess,
okay,
this is,
imagine this is the Google model.
And so,
yeah,
I'm not gonna go into it here,
but stable diffusion kind of really kicked off because it was more efficient
and slightly higher quality,
but it's using a encoder - decoder with attention kind of architecture,
and I guess it's not really showing it here.
I mean,
this is like their overall diagram.
Maybe it's kind of represented here,
but it's reducing the size
into kind of like a smaller embedding space,
denoising and then upscaling
to the higher resolution.
But it's also,
you know, able
to condition on images,
some other representation,
some kind of
semantic map or text,
so you could condition
it on a lot of different things
and it seems to work well.
So I thought I'd throw this picture in because I was trying to create it
and I wasn't successful
and I think the way it failed is kind of interesting.
So on Dali 3 now,
they have this new feature.
So my original prompt was this.
So I wanted to use it as the transition in the slide
where it's a Victorian butcher dressed,
cranking a meat grinder,
but math symbols
are going in
and nice pictures are falling out.
And so actually what,
this is not my first iteration,
but it was actually
ground meat look kind of disgusting,
so I didn't include that picture.
So the interesting thing about Dali 3
now
is that you can go into it
and you can actually select part of the image.
And so,
and this is where diffusion models also,
you know,
one of their strengths is in painting.
So I just selected all of the ground meat here
and then I tried it again.
And by the way,
remember in Dali 3,
behind the scenes,
it's creating a much more detailed.
So it's using an LLM,
actually using GPT - 4
to create a very detailed prompt that it doesn't even show you
unless you kind
of click on the info button.
So it's interesting how they've trained this more detailed prompt.
And even on the detailed prompt,
it is saying that I want math symbols
going in
and pictures coming out.
And I even masked this and told it to do it again.
But,
you know,
you can think that,
at least in the probability distribution,
apparently it was so far out
of the distribution of having like a meat grinder doing math.
I just couldn't get it.
I couldn't steer it,
you know,
out of this mode,
kind of realistic.
It did draw
a lot of symbols on the meat grinder itself,
funny enough.
You know,
I didn't ask it to,
but I think it's kind
of indicative of that,
you know,
you're playing with these distributions and,
I could not get it out of the,
you know,
the more central mode of,
a picture of a Victorian butcher with a meat grinder.
But you can imagine,
so in - painting
is kind of a easy conditioning process,
right?
So you just mask out this area.
You just provide
the rest of the image with a mask,
the masked area,
and then just do noise
and diffusion on that part,
you know,
conditioned on everything else.
So it's,
you know,
it has a lot of flexibility.
And of course,
they're using it for music
and everything else as well.
Okay,
so if you wanna,
this,
here's the link again.
Let me know if you don't have access
to the blog post.
I think it helps make the chapter a little bit
more readable too.
And then there's a CVPR 2023 last year.
There was a tutorial,
it's like a five - hour tutorial.
If you wanna go,
you know,
it starts from,
like where I started,
but it goes pretty quickly into the,
into more details.
There's another version,
the next version at
CVPR this year.
They're doing it again as well.
All right,
so,
okay,
so that's it for diffusion.
So next time it's,
I'm doing graph neural networks and then reinforcement
learning.
And again,
I'm gonna try to focus on like
RLHF because I know at least half the class is taking reinforcement
learning.
So,
and then please for the leaderboard people,
work with Xavier
and get that slide or two together.
All right,
thank you.